<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A booke of Bertram the priest, concerning the body and blood of Christ written in Latin to Charles the Great, being Emperour, aboue eight hundred yeeres agoe. Translated and imprinted in the English tongue. Anno Dnj. 1549.</title>
            <title>De corpore et sanguine Domini. English</title>
            <author>Ratramnus, monk of Corbie, d. ca. 868.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20752</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115659</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850877</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850877</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16112</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10472)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16112)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1360:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A booke of Bertram the priest, concerning the body and blood of Christ written in Latin to Charles the Great, being Emperour, aboue eight hundred yeeres agoe. Translated and imprinted in the English tongue. Anno Dnj. 1549.</title>
                  <title>De corpore et sanguine Domini. English</title>
                  <author>Ratramnus, monk of Corbie, d. ca. 868.</author>
                  <author>Lynde, Humphrey, Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>And now the third time published for the profit of the reader. 1623.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[38], 80, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Dawson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bertram the priest = Ratramnus.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: De corpore et sanguine Domini.</note>
                  <note>A different translation from that of William Hugh.</note>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: Humfrey Lynde.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Transubstantiation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Real presence --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16112:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16112:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BOOKE OF BERTRAM THE Prieſt, Concerning the Body and Blood of Chriſt, Written in Latin to <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, being Emperour, aboue eight hundred yeeres agoe.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated and imprinted in the Engliſh Tongue. A<hi rend="sup">nno</hi> D<hi rend="sup">n</hi>j. 1549.</p>
            <p>And now the third time publiſhed for the profit of the Reader. 1623.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Dawſon.</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16112:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16112:2"/>
            <head>TO MY MVCH HONORED FRIEND, S<hi rend="sup">R</hi> WALTER PYE, Knight, the KINGS Ma<hi rend="sup">ties</hi> Atturney of the Court of <hi>Wards</hi> and <hi>Liveries.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue nothing of my owne worthy of your loue; but behold a great Worke of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mans in this little Volume, I
<pb facs="tcp:16112:3"/>
Dedicate vnto you. It was preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a great Emperour, <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> and by him it was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved as heire generall to the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers: The Author is now after <hi>800.</hi> yeeres queſtioned for his birth-right, and the Polemicall Writers of this Age are not as yet agreed whether he ſpurious or legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate. I hope the Preface follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (his very enemies being Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) will free him from that impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. His revennue is the doctrine of the bleſſed Sacrament, ancient and hereditarie: His tenure is in Capite of the Lord <hi>Paramount.</hi> My ſuite is an Information may be exhibited againſt his accuſers, and if you ſee no iuſt cauſe whereof they
<pb facs="tcp:16112:3"/>
doe accuſe him, let your wonted Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice decree him for the right heire; if otherwiſe, let him ſtand or fall according to your Wiſedome, and his owne worth, and in doing him this right, you ſhall oblige me with the reſt of your favours faithfully to loue you and yours.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>HVMFREY LYNDE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16112:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16112:4"/>
            <head>The Preface to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE great contention that was betwixt the two Women,<note place="margin">1 Kings Chap. 3.</note> who ſhould be the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the liuing childe, was by <hi>Salomon</hi> eaſily decided, and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving childe by his wiſedome was reſtored to the right Mother. If Truth &amp; Peace had ioyned hands with <hi>Rome</hi> and vs, Wiſedome her ſelfe would haue iuſtified her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and our Adverſaries would haue reſolued this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (which without all queſtion is to be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) that <hi>Bertram</hi> was the true Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this fruitfull iſſue, and his
<pb facs="tcp:16112:5"/>
Doctrine was the Tenet of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers and the Church his Mother.</p>
            <p>But ſuch is the condition of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that although the true ſonne may as eaſily bee knowne by his voice as <hi>Iacob</hi> was from <hi>Eſau;</hi> yet the Mother that bred this childe would make him an <hi>Eſau,</hi> and ſupplant him of his birth-right; the wombe that brought him forth diſclaymes his Doctrine, the Church that gaue him ſucke out of her two Breaſts, the two Teſtaments, denies him entertainment: and yet behold the Mother of the child, and this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Mother do ſympathize: The Mother of the child although ſhe were a ſtrumpet, yet would ſhe by no meanes ſuffer her ſon to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, nor accept of a dead child, although it was preſented to her as her owne. This Authors Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:16112:5"/>
(although at that time of his birth ſhe had loſt much of her wonted modeſtie) yet would ſhe not agree, to haue her bleſſed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Sacrament to be divided and given by the halues, yea, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though what was offered her, Chriſt told her it was her body; yet by no meanes would ſhe allow of the dead Letter which killeth, but of the quickning Spirit which giueth life.</p>
            <p>Here we ſee the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is auncient, not her errors. We ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge ſhee was a Mother Church, and had ſometimes <hi>Kings for Nurſing Fathers, and Queenes for Nurſing Mothers:</hi> yea, behold this man <hi>Bertram,</hi> had a King, a great King, <hi>Charlemaine the Great,</hi> to his Nurſing Father, and the Romiſh Church, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the faireſt amongſt women, gaue him milke out of her ſacred
<pb facs="tcp:16112:6"/>
Breaſts, as a Nurſing Mother.</p>
            <p>If there be any remembrance left to Parents for their childrens me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>Mother, behold thy Sonne.</hi>] If there be any meanes left for chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to relieue their blind and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed Parents. <hi>Sonne, behold thy Mother.</hi>] Such is our charitie to the bond-woman &amp; her children, that we pittie them, we pray for them, yea, in this Subiect of the reall preſence; We heartily wiſh, that men had not ſtudied ſo much to be open where the Scripture is ſilent, and that curious wits had not beene wiſe aboue ſobrietie, to haue ſearched into the wayes of the Lord, which are paſt finding out.<note place="margin">B: <hi>Andrewes</hi> againſt <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. cap.</hi> 1.</note> That which <hi>Durandus</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to haue ſaid, doth not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like vs; <hi>We heare the Word, we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ſound, we know not the manner, we beleeue the Preſence, we beleeue (I ſay) the Preſence as well
<pb facs="tcp:16112:6"/>
as they, concerning the manner of the Preſence, we doe not vnadviſedly define, nay more, we doe not ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulouſly enquire: no more then we doe in Baptiſme, how the blood of Chriſt cleanſeth vs, no more then we doe in the Incarnation of Chriſt, how the divine nature is vnited to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, we reckon it amongst the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and indeed the</hi> Euchariſt <hi>is a myſterie, the remaynders whereof ſhould be conſumed with fire, that is, (as the Fathers doe elegantly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it) which ſhould be adored by faith, not debated by reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to come to the Author and his Authoritie. Behold, after 800. yeares ſilence in the graue, there is riſen this Champion, to confute this new borne Bratt <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.</hi> All the credit that I haue, or am like to haue in the Church of God, I will ingage it vpon the worth of this little Tract. A worke
<pb facs="tcp:16112:7"/>
not powred forth vpon Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but compoſed with mature deliberation, being required ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto by <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour, (neither was it likely, that <hi>ſo great an Eagle as</hi> Charlemayne <hi>would conſult with flyes</hi>) in whom it was hard to ſay whether Learning or Magnificence had the vpperhand: and for theſe later times, let the iudgement of that famous Biſhop and Martyr, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ridley</hi> informe vs, of whom I may truly ſay what <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> did of <hi>Nepotian (Pectus ſuum Bibliothecam fecerat Chriſti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierom ad Paulinum.</note> 
               <hi>nec do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leat Eccleſia quod talem amiſerit, ſed gaudeat quod talem habuerit,</hi>) who publiquely honored this Treatiſe in his Diſputations at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and privatly bequeathed it as a Legacy to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Brookes,</hi> affirming it to be the firſt meanes of his converſion, and reducement from the common er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the Roman Church.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16112:7"/>But behold the Authoritie of this Man, and the dexteritie of his ſubiect, is ſo great an eye-ſore to our Adverſaries, that they cannot with any patience reflect vpon him: Here ſhall you ſee <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> againſt <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi> but both againſt <hi>Iuda;</hi> here you ſhall ſee Iurors and Iudges reconciled, as <hi>Pilot</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> but both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Bertram:</hi> Will you haue him brought as <hi>Paul</hi> was before the Councell, &amp; ſet before them; <hi>Behold the Man.</hi> The Iudge doth harken, the Councellers be ſilent, the Cryer biddeth peace, all the people are attentiue to know the cauſe whereof they would accuſe him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> the Foreman of the Inqueſt, he ſaith,<note place="margin">Bellarm: de ſcript: Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſt. Tom. <hi>7.</hi> fol. <hi>121.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That</hi> Bertram <hi>the Prieſt liued aboue</hi> 800. <hi>yeares ſince, and was the firſt that brought in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
<pb facs="tcp:16112:8"/>
the Reall preſence, but ſayth he,</hi> Paſchaſius Ratbertus, <hi>an Abbot wrote fully and freely of that ſubiect againſt him.</hi> So then we ſee him here confeſſed for the Author, but oppoſed for his Doctrine, if <hi>Bellarmine</hi> haue ſpoken the truth, beare witnes w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> him of the truth. Onely let me tell you, I haue read that whole Tract of <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> Printed by them, and there I finde he writes of the Reall preſence, he mentioneth two Sacraments, and maintaines the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion in both kinds, but of <hi>Bertram</hi> in his whole Treatie <hi>ne</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quidem,</hi> he makes not ſo much as mention of him: and this mine eyes haue witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Truth againſt the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of 3. <hi>Converſ. part.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note>The ſecond is <hi>F: Parſons:] Bertram</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>was wholy of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Religion, and ſo liued and ſo died aboue eight hundred yeeres agoe,
<pb facs="tcp:16112:8"/>
though after his death ſome of</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarius <hi>followers, did forge a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Pamplet in his name againſt the Reall preſence of Chriſts bodie, as favouring the</hi> Berengarian <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie:</hi> Here then we haue the man confeſſed but not this Doctrine: I wonder theſe two Elders li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo neere together in <hi>Rome,</hi> were ſo farre aſunder in opinion; Surely they agree like the two El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders againſt <hi>Suſanna,</hi> both ioyned together to accuſe the Innocent, &amp; both out of their owne mouths muſt receiue the like judgement.</p>
            <p>The third] <hi>About the yeare</hi> 806.<note place="margin">Lib: conſenſ: omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> atat: de verit: Chi: in Euchar: centen: <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Delirarecoepit Bertramus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retius</hi>). This man acknowledgeth <hi>Bertram</hi> for the Author, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes him for an old Dotard.</p>
            <p>The fourth:] <hi>Langdailius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Langd: lib. <hi>3</hi> Cath: confut:</note> 
               <hi>He af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, That though in ſome things he tranſgreſſed the forme of wordes, yet he holdes correſpondencie with
<pb facs="tcp:16112:9"/>
the Catholique Roman Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this mans ſaying, I ſee no cauſe why <hi>Bertram</hi> deſerved a Writ to priviledge his dotage.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">De viſib. Monarch. Eccleſ. lib. <hi>7.</hi> An. <hi>816.</hi> &amp;c.</note>The fifth:] <hi>Sanders he ſaith, That vnder the name of</hi> Bertram, <hi>there is a Booke extant of the</hi> Euchariſt, <hi>which is ſayd to haue bin lately writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, or deviſed by ſome of</hi> Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius <hi>followers, for that there was no ſuch Doctrine then read, or knowne in that time of his liuing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the <hi>Sacram: cap.</hi> 1 <hi>fol.</hi> 23</note>The ſixth:] <hi>Reynolds the Prieſt ſaith, toward</hi> 800 <hi>yeeres after Chriſt, one</hi> Bertram, <hi>and a little before him one</hi> Scotus <hi>wrote darkly of the truth of this Sacrament, but whatſoever the private opinion of</hi> Bertram <hi>was, his publique ſpeeches and writings ſounded ſo ill in the eares of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques of that age, that</hi> Paſchaſius <hi>an Abbot made a very learned Booke in refutation of him.</hi> Theſe two hold together like a rope of Sand,
<pb facs="tcp:16112:9"/>
the one ſaith, <hi>Bertram</hi> did write but obſcurely, the other ſaith, It was not <hi>Bertram,</hi> but ſome obſcure Authors; the one ſaith, there was no ſuch doctrine publiſhed in that age, the other ſaith, that <hi>Scotus</hi> at that time wrote darkly, as <hi>Bertram</hi> did on the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh, and eight:<note place="margin">Poſſeu: prefi ad Lect: tom. <hi>1.</hi> apparat. Sixt: Sen. prafat. in Bibl.</note>] <hi>Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colampadius, vnder the name of</hi> Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram <hi>wrote this booke to</hi> Charles <hi>the Great, ſayth</hi> Poſſevinus <hi>and</hi> Sixtus Senenſis.</p>
            <p>The ninth:<note place="margin">Greg: lib. <hi>1.</hi> de praf. Chi: in Euch. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>] <hi>The Worke is ſpuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and tainted with the Leven of</hi> Berengarius <hi>hereſie, ſaith</hi> Gregory de Valentia. Theſe alſo might well agree, if they could reconcile the times and their different opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions: for <hi>Berengarius</hi> liued about ſix hundred yeares agoe, and <hi>Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colampadius</hi> about a hundred. But if either <hi>Berengarius</hi> followers, or <hi>Oecolampadius</hi> himſelfe wrote this
<pb facs="tcp:16112:10"/>
Tract of <hi>Bertrams,</hi> it muſt needs be that <hi>Paſchafius Ratbertus,</hi> who wrote againſt this Treatiſe 800. yeares agoe (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> &amp; <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds</hi> doe affirme) did write by the Spirit of Prophecie againſt <hi>Beren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garius</hi> followers, &amp; <hi>Oecolampadius</hi> long before they were borne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of Chriſt. <hi>Sacr.</hi> in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</note>The tenth:] D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Heskius</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Bertram in the time of</hi> Charles, <hi>wrote of the Sacrament ſuſpitiouſly, and yet in ſuch ſort, as no man could be certaine, what hee aſſuredly meant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">De Ador: Euchar: cap. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note>The eleventh:] <hi>Eſpencaeus</hi> ſaith, That <hi>Bertram wrote a Booke to</hi> Charles <hi>the Emperour, of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; yet in the iudgement of thoſe that favour his error, he doth intangle both his cauſe and the minde of the Reader, and although he citeth many of the ancient Fathers, yet one while he ſeemeth a Catholique, another while of another opinion.</hi> Theſe two
<pb facs="tcp:16112:10"/>
are nere to reconciliation, for they both agree vpon the certaintie of the Author, but condemne the vncertaintie of his doctrine.</p>
            <p>The twelfth:] <hi>Trithenius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tritenius de Bertr:</note> a man without exception, he ſayth, <hi>That</hi> Bertram <hi>the Prieſt was exceedingly skilfull in the holy Scriptures, he was ſharpe in wit, famous in ſpeech, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was he leſſe notable in life then in learning; he wrote many famous and excellent workes vnto</hi> Charles the Great, <hi>the brother of</hi> Lotharius <hi>the Emperour; he wrote a praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Booke,</hi> (to wit) <hi>one Booke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Body and Blood of the Lord; he flouriſhed in the dayes of</hi> Lotharius <hi>the Emperour, about the yeere of Chriſt</hi> 840.</p>
            <p>You haue heard the great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, what they can ſay againſt this Author. Yet all this while the <hi>Trumpet hath given an vncertaine ſound.</hi> Some (you ſee) denyes
<pb facs="tcp:16112:11"/>
the man as a ſingular Noveliſt, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers acknowledge the Author, but affirme this Worke to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitious, others ſay he held the catholique opinion in the maine, but ſquared in the forme of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſo that hitherto you ſee the Iurors are not agreed among themſelues, and therefore they cannot giue vp their Verdict a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him: Onely this laſt witnes doth beſt reſolue all the former doubts, he ſheweth, that <hi>Bertram</hi> was no dotard, he ſhewes it could not be written by <hi>Berengarius,</hi> or his followers, for he liued &amp; wrote this Worke to <hi>Charles</hi> 200. yeares before his time, he ſhewes he was not ſpurious but the true Author, and by this his teſtimonie doth cleerely exclude <hi>Oecolampadius</hi> for the Author, whoſe writings were not extant when <hi>Tritemius</hi> made his Catalogue of this and other Authors.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16112:11"/>Certainely, if theſe men had beene ſworne to the Truth as well as to the Church, the Foreman of the Inqueſt, and the laſt, would haue reconciled all the reſt.</p>
            <p>You haue heard (Gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) the Popes tenants, his ſworne ſervants, our ſworne enemies, their beſt witneſſes, <hi>Bertrams</hi> worſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers, bound by oath to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Papacy, divided amongſt themſelues. Now liſten and heare their ſoveraigne Iudges giue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and according to their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, let him ſtand or fall in your judgment: And firſt let their Lord chiefe Iuſtice, Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the eyght be heard; for, as he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre, ſo he may not be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted.<note place="margin">Ant. Poſſeu: Appar: Pag. <hi>230.</hi> Tom. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Let not</hi> Bertram <hi>be read</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but with leaue of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolique Sea, and with this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Reader my confute the heretiques by the errors of that booke.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16112:12"/>
The next are the <hi>Roman Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ind: libr. <hi>prohibited Anno 1559</hi> &amp; Trident:</note> 
               <hi>and the Trent Fathers; theſe alſo haue decreed him to be included in the number of Authors prohibited.</hi> So then you haue two principall Iudges, a Pope &amp; a late Councell condemning him, and yet this may be thought a ſtrange thing, that without a legall proceeding, without triall of the partie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hearing him, or his Advocate ſpeake for him, to adiudge him? Is it worſe with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at this day, then it was with Heathen <hi>Rome</hi> in the time of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar?</hi> Behold what <hi>Feſtus</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vernour anſwereth <hi>Pauls</hi> accuſers in the like caſe:<note place="margin">Acts 25. verſ. 16.</note> 
               <hi>It is not the manner of the</hi> Romans <hi>to deliuer any man to dye before that he which is accuſed haue the accuſers face to face, and to haue licence to anſwere for himſelfe concerning the crime layd againſt him.</hi> If <hi>Bertram</hi> had beene arraig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:16112:12"/>
and condemned when he was liuing; if his accuſers had beene brought face to face before the Emperour, there might haue bin ſome pretence, ſome Plea, ſome Record againſt him; but after ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hundred yeares continuance to giue ſentence, and to ſit in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation againſt him as Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tife, Witneſſe and Iudge that is neither allowable in Church nor State.</p>
            <p>Well, what will <hi>Bertram</hi> doe in this caſe? Surely, he will appeale (<hi>as</hi> Paul <hi>did to</hi> Caeſar:) but to whom? Not to one man alone, but to a multitude: not to an ignorant multitude, but to a learned; to a Vniverſitie, not on our ſide (for they would be partiall) but on theirs, the famous Vniverſitie of <hi>Doway</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> there he was a free deniſon, bred and borne, and his requeſt is to be tryed by his
<pb facs="tcp:16112:13"/>
               <hi>Countrie. Since therefore he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to the learned men of</hi> Doway, <hi>to</hi> Doway <hi>let him goe.</hi> Now I pray what will theſe Iudges doe? They heare the Popes ſentence, the Councels decree, the Inquiſitors ſevere Iudgement, they weigh ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly his accuſers reaſons, they examine diligently the Author himſelfe, and finding the former doome too heavie for ſo ſlight er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors committed by him, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale the ſentence, and vpon more mature deliberation had of the Author, and his Doctrine, with the conſent of <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, and the <hi>Duke of</hi> Alba <hi>to all the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Catholiques in his behalfe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this Greeting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ind. Expurg. Belgic: p. <hi>5.</hi> edit. Antw. An. <hi>1571.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Although we care not greatly for this Booke of</hi> Bertrams, <hi>whether it be extant or no, yet becauſe it is often printed, and read of many, and the Heretiques know by a Catalogue of
<pb facs="tcp:16112:13"/>
forbidden bookes, that he was a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Prieſt, and deare vnto</hi> Charles the Great, <hi>and becauſe we Comment vpon other Writers of the ſame age, and extenuate their errors oftentimes by a favourable conſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, by the ſame reaſon wee may allow</hi> Bertram, <hi>and acknowledg him, for there is nothing worthy of reprehenſion in him, ſetting aſide a little obſcuritie in his ſtile, and his ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in vſing ſome darke words and ſentences, which with marginall notes affixed, may manifeſt the true ſence and meaning of the Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then is his laſt definitiue ſentence pronounced; they allow the Author, and they allow the worke, ſo that a right conſtruction be ioyned to his right meaning, and that no miſpriſion may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the parties on both ſides, the Iudges in the particulars haue delivered their Obſervations. <hi>(Viz.)</hi>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:16112:14"/>
               <hi>di) where he ſayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lege in Iudia Expurgat: Belgic. edit. An. <hi>1571.</hi> Viſibiliter. <hi>(1.)</hi> Inviſibiliter. Subſtantia. <hi>(1)</hi> Accidens.</note> (<hi>folio</hi> 1137.) <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiblie; that is to be read and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, ſay they, Inuiſiblie: and where he ſayes (infrà) verſu</hi> 36) <hi>the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the creature which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſecration, remayneth after conſecration, by the ſubſtance is meant</hi> (ſay they) <hi>the Accidents do remaine.</hi> Thus our Adverſaries haue a free diſpenſation to reade him with theſe and the like conditions ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. <hi>It is freely granted, let it be freely accepted.</hi> Now if I ſhould queſtion, how it were poſſible that the ſubſtance of bread ſhould be annihilated, and the accidents remaine without a Subſtance, it were no diſparagement for me not to vnderſtand it, for I doubt not,<note place="margin">Ind. Expurg. Belg: Antw. An. <hi>1571.</hi>
               </note> ſaith the <hi>Index Expurgatorius, but</hi> Bertram <hi>in thoſe times was ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, how the accidents could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly ſubſiſt, without any ſubſtance, which this later age hath moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly
<pb facs="tcp:16112:14"/>
and truely found out;</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Tranſub: lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi> Breve et ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex &amp; ſiue vllo incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum.</note> 
               <hi>Neither is it to be maruailed,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory de Valentia, that ſome ancients haue both thought and writ leſſe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly concerning</hi> Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>and this is an anſwere</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>briefe and ſimple, and no way incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient.</hi> The reaſon (as I conceiue) is given by another of their ſide. <hi>The Doctors of theſe latter times haue attained more vnderſtanding in ſome things then the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dominic. Bannes.</hi> 22. <hi>pag.</hi> 58. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>for they are like children</hi> (ſay they) <hi>ſtanding on the ſhoulders of Gyants, who being lifted vp by the talneſſe of the Gyants, no marvaile if they ſee further then they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true indeede, that this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine in <hi>Bertrams</hi> time had not that full ſtreame and generall cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant as it had in the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers time before it, as it appeares in his Preface to <hi>Charles the Great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16112:15"/>Neither was this Doctrine broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by a <hi>Noveliſt,</hi> for then the Emperour would haue condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, or at leaſt-wiſe haue confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, neither did he alone in this time hold this doctrine, for <hi>Scotus</hi> about that time wrote a Booke of the ſame ſubiect.<note place="margin">
                  <p>Alcui: lib. de divinis offic. Beda lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Tabernac. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Carol. Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas in Epiſt. ad Alcuinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lib. <hi>2.</hi> de offic. pa. <hi>100</hi> Edit. Coloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſi.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alcui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> Tutor vnto the Emperour, <hi>Venerable Bede,</hi> &amp; <hi>Charles</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror himſelfe, did all ſavour one thing, and ſpeake one thing at the ſame time with the ſame Author. Neither did he in this opinion leane to his owne witt, but <hi>did purſue and tread in the foot-ſteps of the holy and ancient Fathers.</hi> Such was his anſwer to the Emperour, and ſuch will his Doctrine mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it ſelfe vnto the Reader. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could this Doctrine be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Petigian: in</hi> 4. <hi>Sentent. d.</hi> 10. 9. 1. <hi>art.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 353.</note> for ſayth <hi>Petigian for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares after Chriſt and more, there was no Hereſie in the Church
<pb facs="tcp:16112:15"/>
concerning the Reall preſence, as it appeares</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>both by ſacred Councels, and doctrine of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, if this Author had bin ſingle in his opinion, as he was ſingular, how comes it to paſſe, that in theſe times he is ſo much oppoſed, and in former ages, hee was not confuted? To queſtion the Writers, to obſcure the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, to mutilate their Bookes, argues a diſtruſt of the truth and goodneſſe of the cauſe, and as <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius</hi> ſometimes anſwered the <hi>Gentiles. To intercept our Writings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Arnib: ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and to drowne our Authors, it makes no defence for your Gods, but rather it argues your feare leaſt the Truth ſhould appeare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, how comes it to paſſe, that there is ſuch difference of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions concerning this man? how is it that their kingdome is
<pb facs="tcp:16112:16"/>
ſo much divided againſt it ſelfe, that they cannot by <hi>any glue of Concord</hi> (as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>nor bond of vnitie be conioyned?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyp: lib. <hi>3.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> Some hold of <hi>Paul,</hi> ſome of <hi>Apollos,</hi> ſome allow the Booke, others deny the Author: Is the Worke man and the Worke divided? Is the Author of the Booke commended, &amp; the Booke it ſelfe condemned? Is this the wiſedome and pollicie of the Church, to <hi>cry ſome one thing, ſome another,</hi> like the common <hi>Craftſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> for their great <hi>Diana of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians?</hi> Theſe things were much to be wondred at, eſpecially by one that wants perhaps the lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, perhaps the knowledge, to ſearch into theſe doubtfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, but that the ingenuous confeſſion of <hi>Eraſmus</hi> will ſatisfie a further jnquiſition. <hi>It is plainely found</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that many things in</hi> Luthers <hi>Bookes are condemned for
<pb facs="tcp:16112:16"/>
hereticall, which in the Bookes of</hi> Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard <hi>and</hi> Auſten <hi>are read for holy and Orthodox.</hi> Agreeable to that ſaying of <hi>Maldonats,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maldon: Comment. in Ioh. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> expounding a place of Scripture: <hi>Although I haue no other Author</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for my expoſition, yet I allow it rather then that of</hi> Auſtens <hi>and others, (though it be moſt probable) becauſe this of mine croſſeth more the ſenſe of the</hi> Calviniſts.</p>
            <p>Thus then to end with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (with whom I began:<note place="margin">Iſid. Pleuſit. lib. <hi>3.</hi> epiſt. <hi>408.</hi>
               </note>) <hi>Shee is like a Woman fallen from her ancient happineſſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining onely ſome ſignes thereof: ſhe hath the Sheaths and Caskets where the Ornaments lay, but the goods themſelues ſhe is ſpoyled off.</hi> Hence it is that wee are departed from their Church, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſometimes departed out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> or as S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten</hi> from the <hi>Maniches:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Math. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. <hi>49.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from them in body, they firſt
<pb facs="tcp:16112:17"/>
departed from vs in minde: we from them by place, they from vs by faith: we haue left with them the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the walls; they haue left with vs the foundations of the Scriptures: We are departed from them in the ſight of man; they are departed from vs in the iudgement of GOD.</hi> And as concerning this Author which I here preſent vnto you,<note place="margin">Ierom: Epiſt. <hi>126.</hi> ad Euagr:</note> I will ſay, as S. <hi>Ierom</hi> anſwered <hi>Euagrius,</hi> who deſiring his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he were the holy Ghoſt; S. <hi>Ierom,</hi> when he had ſhewed him the iudgement of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Fathers,</hi> of whom ſome thought <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> a Man, ſome an Angell: <hi>You haue</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what I haue heard, what I haue read touching</hi> Melchiſedec, <hi>to bring forth the witneſſes it was my part, let it be yours to iudge of the credit of the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16112:17"/>Behold <hi>(Gentle Reader)</hi> the Worke-man and the Worke: I haue cited the opinions of the Moderne Writers, and of the beſt concerning this Author, it is your part to iudge of the credit of them: it was my part to ſummon their apparance for the tryall of the partie, it is your part to iudge of the ſufficiencie of their proofe, &amp; their good agreement amongſt themſelues. You haue the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor aboue 800. yeares continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, you haue his doctrine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue 1500. yeares: if his proofe make it not good, we will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clayme both the Author, and his Doctrine.</p>
            <p>If ſuch a light did ſo ſhine when the Church was ſo much dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and obſcured with the miſts of Ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, pittie it were but this <hi>Lampe</hi> ſhould receiue a new <hi>Light</hi> (by <hi>reprinting of him</hi>) which the
<pb facs="tcp:16112:18"/>
Iniquitie of the times hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>Briefely, all that I can ſay of the Author, is this; That which <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius Lyrinenſis</hi> ſpake of <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> may very fitly be attributed to him; <hi>His words are ſenſes, his ſenſes victories:</hi> and as concerning the Worke, and the exquiſite per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof, I will ſay in two words: <hi>Exegit Monumentum:</hi> It may ſtand, (and long may it ſtand a Monument to after Ages) that he may be juſtified in his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and cleare when he is jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:16112:18"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>Bertram</hi> the Prieſt, his Preface, concerning <hi>the body and blood of the</hi> LORD, written to Charles <hi>the great,</hi> being Emperour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am commanded by you (famous Prince) to declare vnto your Highneſſe, What iudgement I am of, concerning the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the Bodie and Blood of Chriſt. Certaine it is, that as this commandement, doth well beſeeme your magnificall and Princely eſtate: ſo is it a moſt hard thing to be performed by my poore and ſmall power. For what is
<pb facs="tcp:16112:19"/>
more meete for your Kingly Providence and government, than in reſpect of your ſelfe to be vniverſally wiſe, concerning his holy myſteries, who hath vouchſafed you worthy of the Kingly ſeate: and in reſpect of your Subiects, not to ſuffer them to thinke divers things, concerning the bodie and blood of Chriſt, in which, doubtleſſe, conſiſteth the whole ſumme of Chriſtian Redemption? For while ſome of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full affirme, that the myſterie or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the body and blood of Chriſt (which is daily celebrated and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the Church) is done vnder no fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, and vnder no cover at all, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>med vnder the naked manifeſtation &amp; ſhew of the truth it ſelfe: and againe, while other ſome teſtifie, that theſe things are conteined vnder the figure of the myſtery, and that it is one thing which appeareth to our bodily ſenſes, and another thing that our faith looketh vpon, it plainly appeareth that there is no ſmall diverſitie and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence amongst them. And whereas the Apoſtle writeth vnto the faithfull people, <hi>That all of them ſhould ſavour one thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>and ſpeake one thing, and that
<pb facs="tcp:16112:19"/>
no ſchiſme ſhould appeare amongſt them,</hi> we muſt needs ſay, that they are by no ſmall ſchiſme divided, and rent aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, who not thinking the ſelfe ſame things doe ſpeake diverſly of the myſterie of the bodie and blood of Chriſt. Wherefore your Kingly Maieſtie and Highneſſe being provoked no doubt with the zeale of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (though perhaps not quietly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently conſidering of theſe things) and deſiring alſo, that all men ſhould (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Apoſtles Commandement) <hi>thinke and ſpeake one thing</hi> doth dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſearch for the myſterie and ſecret of truth, that ſo you may call backe ſuch therevnto, as haue wandred and ſtrayed. Wherevpon alſo it commeth to paſſe, that you diſdaine not, to demand and aske the truth of this matter, even of very poore and baſe men, perſwading your ſelfe, that the myſterie of ſo great a ſecret, cannot be knowne, but by inſpiration and revelation from God, who having no reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſheweth forth the light of his truth, by whomſoever he himſelfe hath choſen to ſo great a matter. Now, as it is very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant for me poore man, to obey your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement:
<pb facs="tcp:16112:20"/>
ſo I confeſſe it is a very hard matter for me, to diſpute and reaſon of a matter ſo farre eſtranged from mans vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and ſenſes, and into which a man cannot pearſe or enter, but by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and teaching of the holy Spirit. Wherefore, I being at this preſent ſubiect, to your Highneſſe commandement, and yet truſting and cleaving to the ayde and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of him of whom we will ſpeake, will aſſay by what words I can to open my iudgement concerning this matter, not leaning in the treatie thereof to mine owne wit, but purſuing and treading in the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of the holy and auncient Fathers.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16112:20"/>
            <head>HERE BEGIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Booke of <hi>Bertram</hi> the Prieſt, touching the body and blood of the Lord: which he wrote to <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, being Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Highneſſe Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy demandeth,<note place="margin">1 Two que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions.</note> whether that the body and blood of Chriſt, which in the Church is receiued by the mouth of the faithfull, bee done in a myſtery, or in truth and verity? that is to ſay, whether it containe ſome ſecret thing, which is euident to the eyes of faith onely: or whether, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the vaile or couerture of any my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, the bodily ſight, doe outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16112:21"/>
behold that, which the ſight of the minde doth inwardly looke vpon, ſo that whatſoeuer is done appeareth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly or no? And this is the firſt queſtion. The other is whether it be that very body, that was borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> that ſuffered, that died, that was buried, and that riſing againe, &amp; aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding vp into heauen, ſitteth now on the right hand of the Father or no?</p>
            <p>Now let vs looke into the firſt of theſe two queſtions: and leſt wee be letted with ambiguity and doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, let vs define what a figure is, and what the truth is, that ſo beholding and perceiuing ſome certainty, wee may know, whither wee ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the courſe of our reaſoning.</p>
            <p>A figure is a certaine ſhadow, by certaine vailes &amp; couertures as it were, that is to ſay, darkely declaring the thing, which it intendeth to manifeſt: as for example, when wee minde to ſpeake of Gods Word, we call it bread: ſo in the Lords Prayer wee deſire to haue <hi>daily bread,</hi> giuen vs. Alſo when Chriſt in the Goſpell ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.11</note> ſaying:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16112:21"/>
               <hi>I am the living bread which came downe from heaven.</hi> Likewiſe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.51.</note> when hee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth himſelfe a <hi>Vine,</hi> and his Diſciples <hi>branches,</hi> ſaying, <hi>I am the true Vine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 15.1.5</note> 
               <hi>and yee are the branches.</hi> For all theſe ſayings, ſeeme to ſpeake one thing, and yet meane another thing.</p>
            <p>As for that which wee call verity, or truth, it is the declaration of a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and plaine matter, which is not couered with any ſhew of ſhadowes, but inſinuated and delivered, with pure and open (or to ſpeak more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) with naturall ſignifications: as when it is ſaid, <hi>That Chriſt being borne of a Virgin, ſuffered death, was crucified,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 1.25 1 Pet. 3.18 1 Cor. 2.2 Ioh. 19.40 &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>dead and buried.</hi> Heere verily is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhadowed, with figures ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couering the ſame, but the truth of the things declared, by the ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of naturall wordes or ſpeeches: neither may we heere vnderſtand any other thing, than that which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and expreſſed. But it is not ſo in the former ſentences, for neither is Chriſt the <hi>bread,</hi> ſubſtantiallly, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is Chriſt a <hi>Vine</hi> ſubſtantially, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16112:22"/>
are the Apoſtles branches ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially: wherefore in theſe latter ſpeeches there is a figure, and in thoſe former, the truth (that is to ſay, a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and open ſignification) is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by narration or plaine ſpeech. Now let vs returne to thoſe things (that is, to <hi>the body and blood of Chriſt</hi>) for whoſe theſe points haue been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and vttered. Truly if that great myſtery be celebrated and done vnder no myſtery at all, then it is not rightly called a myſtery, becauſe that cannot be called a myſtery, or ſecret, wherein there is no hidden thing, and wherein there is no matter remooued from our bodily ſenſes, and wherein there is nothing covered, with ſome vaile or couerture. But that bread, which by the Miniſtery of the Prieſt, is now become the body of Chriſt, doth ſhew one thing outwardly to mans ſenſes, and ſoundeth another thing inwardly to the mindes of the faithfull: Outwardly indeed the form of bread, which it had before, is ſet out, the colour thereof is ſhewed, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16112:22"/>
the ſavour thereof received and taſted. But inwardly a thing farre differing, yea and much more precious, and excellently is ſhewed and ſet forth, and I ſay, it is much more precious and excellent, becauſe it is heauenly, and becauſe it is diuine: I meaning hereby that Chriſts body is manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, which is either ſeen, or receiued, or eaten, not with the ſenſes &amp; facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or power of the fleſh, but with the eye and ſight of a faithfull or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving minde. The wine alſo which by the Prieſt through conſecration, is become the Sacrament of Chriſts blood, ſetteth forth one thing out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and containeth an other thing inwardly. For what other thing is ſuperficially and outwardly locked vp, then the ſubſtance of wine? Taſte it, and it ſavoureth and ſmacketh wine: ſmell it, and it ſmelleth wine: looke vpon it, and thou mayſt behold the colour of wine. But if a man do conſider it inwardly, then it being, not the liquor of wine, but the liquor of Chriſt blood, ſo ſavoreth to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16112:23"/>
beleevers minds while it is taſted, and is ſo acknowledged while it is beheld, and is ſo proved to be, whileſt it is ſmelled.</p>
            <p>It is manifeſt that theſe things are ſo, ſeeing no man can deny them to be true, becauſe the Bread and the Wine is figuratiuely Chriſts body &amp; blood. For outwardly and according to that which is ſeene, neither is any kind or ſhew of fleſh knowne to be in that Bread, nor any drop of blood ſhewed forth in the Wine, and yet for all that, after the myſticall conſecration, the Bread is no more called Bread, nor the Wine Wine, but both of them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether are called the body and blood of Chriſt. For if (according to ſome mens mindes) nothing were in this matter taken figuratiuely, but the whole were conſidered and looked vpon in veritie or truth, then ſhould faith worke nothing at all therein; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that no ſpirituall thing ſhould be performed, but looke whatſoever the thing it ſelfe were, even that whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhould be taken, according to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16112:23"/>
body, and a mans fleſhly vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> And ſeeing that <hi>faith</hi> (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith) <hi>is the argument and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſuch things as appeare not,</hi> that is to ſay, not of ſuch ſubſtances as are ſeene, but of ſuch as are not ſeene, we ſhall then in this action receiue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing according to faith, becauſe that we diſcerne and iudge of all that is in it, according to our bodily ſenſes. And what I pray you can be more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd then to take Bread to be fleſh, and to affirme, that Wine is blood? And a myſtery that cannot be, in which there is no ſecret or hidden thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined. And how can it be ſaid, to be Chriſts body and blood, in which it is not known, that there is any change made?</p>
            <p>Now every alteration and change,<note place="margin">He proueth by three ſorts of change, that there is no change made in the elements of the Supper.</note> is either made from that thing which actually it is not, into that which actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally it is: or els when it is changed from that which it is, into that, which it is not: or from that which it is, to wit, in reſpect of quality, to that which it is, in reſpect of qualitie, though
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16112:24"/>
changed perhaps into another quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. But in this Sacrament, if onely the truth be conſidered in ſimplicitie and plaineneſſe, and not another thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved, than that which is beheld, no change can be knowne to be made. For neyther hath it paſſed from that which it was not,<note place="margin">The firſt kinde of change.</note> into ſomewhat that is, as ſuch a paſſage and change is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times made in growing things: for whereas they were not before, they to the end they might be paſſed, from not being, to that which is to be, or to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But this paſſage, or change falleth not out here, becauſe that the Bread and Wine, were, before they paſſed into the Sacrament of the body and blood of Chriſt.<note place="margin">The ſecond kinde of change.</note> Neither yet can there be here, that paſſage or change, which is made from that which it is, to that which it is not, which change falleth out in things that through defect ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a decay or fall. For whatſoever doth decay, was firſt and had it being, becauſe that thing can not ſuffer a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay or deſtruction, which never was. And yet, neither can this paſſage or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16112:24"/>
change be knowne to be made in this matter, becauſe that according to truth, that very kinde or ſhape of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which is before, is knowne ſtill to remaine. Moreover,<note place="margin">The third kinde of change.</note> that change which is made, from that which is, to that which is, which change appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſpecially in things, that ſuffer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie and varietie of qualities, as for example, when that which was blacke is turned into white, neither can that change I ſay be knowne to be made here: for nothing can be here found to be changed, either in touching, or in taſt, or in colour, or in favour. Therefore if nothing be changed herein, it is not then any other thing than what it was before. But it is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, for the Bread is become Chriſts body, and the wine his blood, for ſo he himſelfe ſaith: <hi>Take ye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 26.26. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>and eate ye, This is my body:</hi> and ſpeaking of the Cup, he ſayth likewiſe: <hi>This is the blood of the new Testament, which ſhall be ſhed for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore they, that in this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will take nothing figuratiuely, but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16112:25"/>
will haue the whole to conſiſt in the ſimplicitie, and plaineneſſe of truth, muſt be demanded, how, and in what reſpect this change is made, ſo that now they be no more that, which they were before, to wit, Bread and Wine, but are the body &amp; blood of Chriſt? For according to the kind and ſhew of the creature, and the outward forme of viſible things, both of theſe, that is, the Bread &amp; the Wine, haue nothing at all changed in them: and if they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer no change at all, then are they no other thing, but that which they were before.</p>
            <p>Your Highneſſe (moſt noble Prince) perceiveth, whether the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding and mind of thoſe men that thinke o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, proceedeth: for they denie that which men ſuppoſe them to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, and they are proved to deſtroy that which they beleeue. For they doe faithfully confeſſe it, to be the body and blood of Chriſt, and in ſo doing doubtleſſe, they doe now proteſt, that the Bread and the Wine be nor the ſame that they were before, and that if
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16112:25"/>
they be ſome other thing than they were before, that then they haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſome alteration and change.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that this cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, let them tell vs, how, &amp; in what reſpect they are changed, for a man ſhall perceiue nothing, to be bodily &amp; ſubſtantially changed in them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt of neceſſitie confeſſe, either that they are changed, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than bodily and ſubſtantially,<note place="margin">He draweth his reaſon from a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> and ſo by that means that they are not that which in truth they ſeeme to be, but ſome other thing, which according to his owne being, is not ſeene or percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be: or els, if they will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe this, they muſt needs denie it, to be the bodie and blood of Chriſt, which thing is very wicked, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a man to ſpeake, but alſo to thinke.</p>
            <p>But for as much as they doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, both the body and blood of Chriſt to be there: and that this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, but by making a change into a better thing, and that this change is made not corporally or bodily, but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16112:26"/>
ſpiritually: it muſt needs be, that they doe affirme and ſay, that this change is made figuratiuely, becauſe that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the vayle or coverture of bodily Bread, and bodily Wine, there is the ſpirituall body of Chriſt, and his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall blood: not that they are the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtences and beings, of two ſeverall and divers things, that differ betweene themſelues, that is to ſay, of the bodie and of the ſpirit: but becauſe, that the kinde or ſhew of Bread and Wine, is in one reſpect, one and the ſelfe ſame thing, that is, Bread and Wine, and in another reſpect, it is the body and blood of Chriſt. For in reſpect, that both of them are bodily and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially touched, they are the kindes and ſhewes of a bodily creature, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of power, becauſe they are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually done, they are the myſteries of the body and blood of Chriſt.<note place="margin">An argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment taken, from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, &amp; the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs conſider the fountaine of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Baptiſme, which is not without cauſe called the fountaine or welſpring of life, becauſe it reformeth them that be partakers of it, to newneſſe of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16112:26"/>
life, and maketh them,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.4.</note> to liue to righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>which before were dead in treſpaſſes and ſinne.</hi> Hath it this power and force, becauſe, or in reſpect that, the element of water, appeareth, or is ſeene to be? and yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, vnleſſe it had in it a vertue and power to ſanctifie, it were not able to waſh away, the ſpots and filthineſſe of ſinne: and vnleſſe it contained the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor and ſtrength of life, it could at no hand giue life to them that are dead, dead I meane, not in the fleſh or body, but in the ſoule or ſpirit. And yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, if in that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, we haue reſpect to that thing onely, which our bodily ſenſe looketh vpon and comprehendeth, we can ſee nothing, but a moyſt and thinne ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to wit, Water, ſubiect to corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that ſuch a one, as that of and in it ſelfe, hath no other power in it, but to waſh our bodies. But after that the power of the holy Ghoſt, by the conſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Prieſt is come ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, it is then become effectuall and powerfull, to waſh, not our bodies
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16112:27"/>
onely, but our ſoules, and made able alſo, by &amp; through a ſpirituall power, to remoue ſpirituall filthineſſes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold we ſee, that there are in one and the ſelfe ſame element two things, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting, and as it were, ſtriving one of them againſt the other, that is to ſay, we ſee a corruptible thing to giue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption, and a thing that hath not life, to yeeld and giue life alſo. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee know that in this fountaine &amp; welſpring, that is one thing, which the bodily ſenſes may touch and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, and therefore it is changeable and corruptible: and againe, that there is another thing in it, which onely faith can beholde, and that therefore it cannot be corrupted, nor come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to danger of decay. Wherfore if a man would demand, What that is, which outwardly waſheth the body, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that it is nothing but the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but if a man would conſider that which inwardly purgeth, I ſay, that it is a liuely vertue, yea, a vertue, that is able to ſanctifie, yea, a vertue and power that giueth immortalitie.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16112:27"/>
Therefore the water in Baptiſme, is in it owne propertie, a corruptible hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor or liquor, but in myſtery and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall meaning, a wholeſome and healthfull power.</p>
            <p>And even ſo verily the body and blood of Chriſt being outwardly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, is a creature, ſubiect to change and corruption: and yet if a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, the vertue and power of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, it is life in deed, giving immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie to ſuch as be partakers thereof. Therefore the things, that are ſeene, and the things that are beleeved, are not all one. For in reſpect that they are ſeene, they feede the corruptible bodie, they themſelues being corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible: but in reſpect that they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved, they feed our immortall ſoules which ſhall liue for ever, they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues being alſo immortall.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle writing to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> ſayth: <hi>Know ye not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.1.2. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>that all our Fathers were vnder the cloud, and all paſſed through the Sea, and were all Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed vnto Moſes in the Cloud, and in the Sea, and did all eate the ſame ſpirituall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16112:28"/>
meat, and did all drink the ſame ſpirituall drink? for they drunke of the ſpirituall Rocke that followed them: and that rocke was Chriſt.</hi> Hence we perceiue, <hi>that the Sea and the Cloud</hi> both, did ſhewe forth the kinde and figure of Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and that the Fathers of the former Teſtament, were Baptiſed in them, that is, in the Cloud, and in the Sea. Could the Sea, as it was ſeene and thought to be an element, haue in it the power and force of Baptiſme? or could the Cloud, as it ſhewed forth, the groſenes of ſome very thicke ayre, ſanctifie the people? No verily: And yet we dare not, ſith the Apoſtle ſpake in Chriſts name, ſay, that he ſpake not truely when he ſaid, <hi>That our Fathers, were baptiſed in the Cloud and in the ſea.</hi> And although that Baptiſme, did ſhew forth and ſet out, the forme of Chriſts Baptiſme, which at this day is vſed &amp; miniſtred in the Church, yet no wiſe man dare deny (vnleſſe like a mad man he will preſume, to gaineſay the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles words) but that it was Baptiſme, and that our Fathers were therein and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16112:28"/>
thereby Baptiſed. Wherefore neither the Sea nor the Cloud, in reſpect that they were bodily ſubſtances, did ſhew forth or giue out the cleanneſſe of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, but in reſpect that they did inviſibly conteine, the ſanctification of the holy Ghoſt. For there was in them, that is, in the Sea, and in the Cloud, both a viſible forme, which appeared to the bodily ſenſes, and that not in an image or ſhew, but in veritie or truth? &amp; inwardly there ſhined forth in them a ſpirituall power, which appeared not to the eyes of fleſh, but to the ſight &amp; light of the minde or ſoule.</p>
            <p>In like ſort, the <hi>Manna</hi> that was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the people from heaven, and the water alſo that flowed out of the Rocke, were corporall and bodily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and did corporally both feede the people, and giue them drinke alſo, and yet the Apoſtle, calleth that <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> ſpirituall meat, and that Water ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall drinke. And why doth he that? Becauſe there was in theſe bodily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, a ſpirituall power of the word, which did feede and giue drinke, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16112:29"/>
to the minds, then to the bodies of the beleevers. And though that meate and that drinke, did but ſhewe forth the myſterie of that bodie and blood of Chriſt, which was to come (which myſterie the Church doth at this day celebrate and adminiſter) yet the holy Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> affirmeth, <hi>that our Fathers did eate the ſame ſpirituall meate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>and did drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A man will perhaps aske, What he meaneth by this word <hi>(the ſame)</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that he meaneth the very ſelfe ſame thing, which the beleeving peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doe at this day, eate and drinke in the Church of Chriſt. For wee may not vnderſtand divers things thereby, becauſe it is one and the ſelfe ſame Chriſt, who with his owne fleſh fed in the Wilderneſſe, the people that was Baptiſed in the Cloud, and in the ſea, and then made them to drinke of his blood, and that doth now in his Church, feede the beleeving people with the Bread of his body, and make them to drinke of the water of his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16112:29"/>
blood. Which thing the Apoſtle min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to declare, after that he had ſaid, <hi>That our Fathers did eate the ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall meate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.4.</note> 
               <hi>and did drinke the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall drinke,</hi> he preſently added, <hi>For they dranke of the ſpirituall Rocke that followed them, and that Rocke was Chriſt.</hi> And this he doth, that ſo wee might vnderſtand that Chriſt, was in the ſpirituall Rocke in the Wildernes, and gaue vnto the people there, the water of his blood: which Chriſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards offred, even to the people of our age, that bodie that he tooke of the Virgin, and was hanged vpon the Croſſe, for the ſalvation of the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers: from which bodie alſo he pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red forth great abundanc of his blood, by which we ſhould not onely be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, but alſo made drinke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>This verily is a wonderfull matter, ſeeing that Chriſt being incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible &amp; ineſtimable, had not as yet take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him mans nature, nor taſted death, for the ſalvation of the world, nor had redeemed vs by his blood, &amp;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16112:30"/>
yet that our Fathers, did in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, by ſpirituall meate, and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible drinke, eate his body, and drinke his blood, as the Apoſtle is a witneſſe, ſaying; <hi>That our Fathers did eate the ſame ſpirituall meate, and did drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke.</hi> Wee muſt not here ſeeke out our own reaſon or way, by which this might bee performed, but faith muſt be vſed, if wee will know, what was done. For he, that now in the Church, doth by his All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie power, ſpiritually turne, the Bread into the fleſh of his bodie, and the wine into the Water, as it were, of his owne blood, he then alſo inviſibly made, the <hi>Manna</hi> that was given from heaven to become his owne bodie, and cauſed the water ſpringing or flowing out of the Rocke, to become his owne blood.<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.25.</note> Which thing, when <hi>David</hi> did well perceiue, he by the holy Ghoſt, proteſted and plainely affirmed, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>Man did eate the bread of Angels.</hi> For it were a fond thing to thinke, that that bodily <hi>Manna,</hi> which was given to the Fathers, ſhould feede the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16112:30"/>
armies and multitudes of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: or that they doe eate any ſuch meate, who are fed and fatted, as it were, with the dainties of Gods word, here on earth, I mean men. Verily the Pſalmiſt, or rather the holy Ghoſt in the Pſalmiſt ſheweth, either what our fathers received in that heavenly <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na:</hi> or els what the faithfull people ſhould beleeue to be, in the myſterie of Chriſts bodie. In both of them certainely Chriſt is ſignified and ſet forth: which Chriſt both feedeth the ſoules of the beleevers, and is the food and meate of Angels: and yet neither of them are done in corporall taſte, or bodily feeding, but by the power of the ſpirituall word.</p>
            <p>And wee know, becauſe the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt hath declared the ſame, that the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, before he ſuffered, <hi>Tooke Bread, and gaue thankes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.26. &amp;c. 1 Cor. 11.23. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>and gaue it to his Diſciples, ſaying: This is my bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>die which is given for you, doe this in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me. Likewiſe, he tooke the Cup, after he had ſupped, ſaying: This Cup is the New Teſtament in my blood,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16112:31"/>
which ſhall be ſhed for you.</hi> We ſee that Chriſt had not as yet ſuffered, and yet for all that he wrought or made, the myſterie of his body and blood: for wee thinke truely that any faithfull man doubteth whether that Bread be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Chriſts bodie, which he gaue vnto his Diſciples, and ſaid; <hi>This is my bodie which is given for you:</hi> or whether the cup conteineth Chriſtes blood, of which cup our Saviour Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſaide: <hi>This cup is the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my blood, which ſhall be ſhed for you.</hi> Therefore as he could, even a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before he ſuffered, turne the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Bread, and the creature of the Wine, into his owne body, which ſhould ſuffer, and into his own blood, which afterwardes ſhould be ſhed: ſo likewiſe was he able in the Wilderneſſe, to turne the <hi>Manna,</hi> and the water that iſſued out of the Rocke, into his owne fleſh and blood, although that a long time after, both his fleſh was to be ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged on the croſſe for our ſakes, and his blood to be ſhed for the waſhing away of our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:16112:31"/>Here alſo wee ought to conſider, how we muſt vnderſtand that which he himſelfe ſaith:<note place="margin">Ioh 6.53.</note> 
               <hi>Except yee eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man and drinke his blood, yee ſhall not haue life in you.</hi> For hee doth not ſay or meane, that his fleſh, which afterwards hanged on the Croſſe, ſhould bee cut in peeces and parts, and ſo be eaten by his Diſciples, neither yet that his blood which hee ſhould ſhed for the redemption of the world, ſhould bee given vnto his Diſciples for drinke, becauſe it ſhould be a moſt wicked and horrible thing, for his Diſciples either to drinke his blood, or to eate his fleſh, as the vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers did at that time vnderſtand him. Therefore in the words follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he ſaid to his Diſciples, who did not vnbeleevingly, but in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of faith receiue Chriſts wordes, although they could not as then pierce and perceiue how thoſe wordes were to bee vnderſtood: to them, I ſay, he ſaid: <hi>Doth this offend you?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.61.62.</note> 
               <hi>What then if yee ſhould ſee the Sonne of man aſcend vp where he was before?</hi> As though he
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16112:32"/>
ſhould ſay: Thinke not I pray you, that you muſt either bodily eate my fleſh, or bodily drinke my blood, or that my body muſt bee divided into parts to be eaten, or my blood diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to be drunke, ſeeing that after my reſurrection, yee ſhall ſee mee to goe vp into heaven, with the fulneſſe of my whole body and blood: and then ſhall ye vnderſtand, that my very fleſh ſhall not be eaten of the beleevers, as the infidels ſuppoſe, but that the bread and the wine, being turned into the ſubſtance of my body and of my blood, the ſubſtance thereof ſhall bee in a myſtery received by the beleevers. And preſently he addeth.<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.63.</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirit is it</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>which quickeneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing.</hi> He ſaith that the fleſh profiteth nothing at all, after ſuch a forme and manner as the vnbeleevers vnderſtood it, otherwiſe it giveth life, as the faithfull do in a myſtery receiue it. And why this is done, he himſelfe doth manifeſtly declare, when hee ſaith: <hi>It is the ſpirit that quickeneth.</hi> Wherefore there is in this myſterie of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16112:32"/>
the body and blood of Chriſt, a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall opperation and working, that giveth life; without the working whereof, theſe myſteries profit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, becauſe they may indeed feed the bodie, but they cannot feed the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Now then heere ariſeth a queſtion, which while many propound, they ſay and affirme, that theſe things are done, not in a figure or myſtery, but in verity and truth. Which while they affirme, they are found to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and to gaine-ſay the writings of the holy Fathers. Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de doct Chriſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> one of the chiefe Doctors of the Church, in his third booke of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doctrine, writeth thus.<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.53.</note> 
               <hi>Except ye eate</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinke his blood, yee ſhall not haue life in you. Hee ſeemeth to command a wicked thing, and an vngodly act. Wherefore it is a figuratiue ſpeech commanding vs to communicate in the Lords paſſion, and ſweetly and profitably to lay vp this in our memories, that his fleſh was crucified and wounded for our
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16112:33"/>
ſakes.</hi> Here we perceiue, that this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ſaith and affirmeth, that the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the bodie &amp; blood of Chriſt, are vnder a figure celebrated and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the faithfull: for hee ſaith plainely, that it belongeth not to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but is rather a wicked thing, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to eate Chriſts body, or to drink his blood: into which fault they fell, who, not ſpiritually but fleſhly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Lords words in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.66.</note> 
               <hi>Departed or went backe from him, and went or walked no more with him.</hi> The ſame Doctor writing in a certaine Epiſtle to <hi>Boniface</hi> the Biſhop,<note place="margin">Aug. ad Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifa. epiſt.</note> amongſt other things ſaith thus. <hi>Truly we vſe oftentimes to ſpeak thus, that when Eaſter draweth nigh, that to morrow, or the next day after ſhall be the Lords paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whereas hee ſuffered ſo many yeares before, and verily that paſſion or ſuffering was done but once for all. Alſo on the Lords day, that wee call Eaſter day, wee vſually ſay, this day the Lord roſe againe, whereas indeed and truth, ſo many yeares are ſince he roſe againe, already paſt. And why is no man ſo fond and fooliſh, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16112:33"/>
vs ſpeaking thus, as though we had lyed, but onely becauſe wee name thoſe dayes, according to the ſimilitude and likeneſſe of theſe dayes, in which theſe things were done? Inſomuch that it is called the very ſame day, which yet is not in deed the very ſame, but in the revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and turning about of the time is like it: and ſo alſo, that is ſaid to be done vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that day, by reaſon of the celebration and administration of the Sacrament, which is not done vpon that day, but was performed long agoe. Was not Chriſt once offered about that time? And yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, hee is not onely every feaſt of Eaſter, but even every day offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the faithfull people, neither is hee to be deemed a lyar who being asked of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, anſwereth that hee is offered. For if the Sacraments had not a certaine ſimilitude and likeneſſe of thoſe things, of which they are Sacraments, they could not at all be Sacraments: and in reſpect of this very likeneſſe that they haue, they take the very names of the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Wherefore, even as the Sacrament of Chriſts body is after a certaine manner
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16112:34"/>
Chriſts body it ſelfe, and the Sacrament of Chriſts blood, is after a certaine man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Chriſts blood, ſo the Sacrament of faith is faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence we perceiue that Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith, that the Sacrament is one thing, and the things whereof they are Sacraments, is another thing. Now the body, in which Chriſt ſuffered, and the blood that came out of his ſide, are the things of the Sacrament: but the myſteries by which theſe things are repreſented, hee ſaith, they are the Sacraments of the body and blood of Chriſt, which are celebrated and adminiſtred, in remembrance of the Lords paſſion and ſuffering, and that not onely every yeare once, at or about the feaſt of Eaſter, but every day in the yeare. And although the Lord had but one bodie, in which hee ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered once for all, and but one blood, which was ſhed for the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world, yet the Sacraments or elements ſignifying theſe things, haue taken the names of the very things themſelues, inſomuch that they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16112:34"/>
are called the body and blood of Chriſt, being ſo called indeed for the ſimilitude and likeneſſe of the things which they repreſent and ſhew forth, even as the feaſt of Eaſter, which is obſerved every yeare, is called the Paſſeover, and the reſurrection of the Lord, whereas we know that the Lord did but once ſuffer, and but once riſe againe, about that time. And albeit, that theſe very dayes, cannot now be revoked or called backe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are already paſt, yet by their name and title are ſuch dayes called, as in which, the memorie of the Lords ſuffering and reſurrection is rehearſed and celebrated: and this is therefore done, becauſe they haue a certaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance and likeneſſe of theſe very dayes, in which our Saviour once ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and once roſe againe: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon we ſay, this day, or to morrow, or the next day, is the Lords paſſion, or reſurrection, when as theſe dayes, in which theſe things were done, were paſſed many yeares agoe. So we may ſay, that the Lord is offered, when the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16112:35"/>
Sacraments of his ſuffering are cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated and adminiſtred, whereas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed hee was but once for all offered vp in himſelfe, for the ſalvation of the world, as the Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>Chriſt hath ſuffered for vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>leaving vs an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that we ſhould follow his footſteps.</hi> For hee ſaith not, that hee every day offered himſelfe, becauſe he did it but once, but this hee ſaith, that hee hath left vs an example, which is daily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and ſhewed forth to the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, in the myſtery of the Lords bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and blood, to the end that every one that ſhall come or repaire thereto, may know that hee ought to be made a companion with him in his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, the image and liuely picture whereof, hee doth, as it were tarry and wait for, to be exhibited vnto him, in the holy myſteries, according to the ſaying of the Wiſeman in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbes:<note place="margin">Pro. 23.1.</note> 
               <hi>Commeſt thou to a mighty mans table, marke diligently what things are ſet before thee,</hi> knowing that thou thy ſelfe muſt another time prepare ſuch like things. To come to a mightie
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16112:35"/>
mans table, is to bee partaker of the Lords offering, or as wee ſay, of the Lords Supper: and the marking or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering of ſuch things as are ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs is the ſound vnderſtanding or knowledge of the bodie and blood of Chriſt: whereof whoſoever parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, hee muſt know and remember thus much, that hee ought to prepare ſuch precious things, that ſo hee may become a follower of Chriſt in dying with him, the remembrance of whoſe death, he profeſſeth and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, not only in beleeving, but alſo in taſting.</p>
            <p>Againe, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the Hebrewes, ſaith thus:<note place="margin">Heb. 7.26.27.</note> 
               <hi>Verily ſuch an high Prieſt it became vs to haue, as is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, harmleſſe, vndefiled, ſeparated from ſinners, and become higher then the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens: who needed not daily (as thoſe high Priests) to offer vp ſacrifice, firſt for his one ſinnes, and then for the peoples: for the Lord Ieſus Chriſt did this once for all, when hee offered vp himſelfe.</hi> That which he did once, he doth now day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſe and vſe. For he once offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16112:36"/>
vp himſelfe for the ſinnes of the people: and this very ſelfe ſame obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or offering, is every day celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among the faithfull, but yet in a myſtery, that ſo that very thing which the Lord Ieſus Chriſt offring vp him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe once for all, hath fulfilled, may by the celebration &amp; adminiſtration of the myſteries, bee daily performed and done, for the remembrance of his death and paſſion. Neither yet is it falſly ſaid, that the Lord in thoſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries is either offered, or ſuffereth, becauſe they haue a certaine ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude or likeneſſe of his death and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whereof indeed, they are true, and liuely repreſentations. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the very myſteries themſelues are called the Lords bodie, and the Lords blood, becauſe they haue the name of that, or thoſe things whereof they be the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iſodorus, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginum ſiue Etymologia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. de officijs. co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>143.</hi> linea <hi>28.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Iſodorus</hi> in his bookes which hee wrote of the true ſignification of words, ſaith thus: <hi>It is called a ſacrifice, as though a man would ſay, a holy fact or deed, becauſe through myſticall prayer, it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16112:36"/>
is conſecrated and appointed, to, or for the remembrance of the Lords ſuffering. Whereupon, by his authority and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement, we cal it the body and blood of Chriſt becauſe that though it bee made of the fruits of the earth, it is yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſanctified, and ſo become a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Gods ſpirit working inviſibly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: the Sacraament of the bred and cup, the Grecians doe call</hi> Euchariſtia: <hi>that is, if it bee interpreted, good grace, or thankeſgiving. And what is better then the body and blood of Chriſt? Now the bread and wine, are therefore compared and reſembled to the Lords body and boold, becauſe that as the ſubſtance of this viſible bread and wine doth nouriſh, and make cheerfull the outward man: So the Word of God, (which is the living or liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread) being once rightly partaked of, doth recreate and refreſh the mindes of the faithfull.</hi> And this Catholike Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor teacheth vs, that that ſame holy myſtery of the Lords paſſion and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, muſt on our behalfes, or in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of vs, bee done for the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the Lords paſſion. And in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16112:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſo ſaying, he declareth that the Lords paſſion or ſuffering, was onely once done, but that the remembrance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is continually repreſented vnto vs, in thoſe ſame holy rites and ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Whereupon, both the bread that is offered, though it be taken, from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the fruits of the earth, is yet notwithſtanding, while it is ſanctified, changed into Chriſts body: as alſo the wine, though it flow out of the Vine, is yet notwithſtanding, through the ſanctification of the divine myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, become the blood of Chriſt, not viſibly indeed, but (as the aforeſaid Doctor affirmeth) the holy Ghoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſibly working therein. Whereupon alſo they are called, both the body and blood of Chriſt, becauſe they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, not as they are outwardly ſeen or beheld, but as they are ſpiritually made, or become vnto vs, Gods ſpirit working inwardly in vs. And becauſe, that through the inviſible power and grace, they are become a farre other matter vnto vs than viſibly they ſeeme to bee, hee therefore maketh a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16112:37"/>
while hee ſaith, <hi>that the bread and the wine, are therefore compared and reſembled to the Lords body and blood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that as the ſubstance of the viſible bread and wine, doth nouriſh and make chearfull the outward man: ſo the Word of God (which is the living or liuely bread) being once rightly partaked of, doth recreate and refreſh the mindes of the faithfull.</hi> Now in ſpeaking thus, hee moſt plainely confeſſeth, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver outward thing is received in the Sacrament of the Lords body and blood, all that is fitted and applyed to the refreſhing of the bodie. But the Word of God, which is the inviſible bread, being inviſibly in the ſame Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, doth through the partaking thereof, by quickening the mindes of the faithfull inviſibly feed them.</p>
            <p>The ſame Doctor alſo ſaith:<note place="margin">Iſidorus, loco ſupra citato.</note> 
               <hi>It is a Sacrament, when it is celebrated or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſtred: as when a thing is ſo done, that the ſelfe ſame thing may be vnderſtood or perceived to ſignifie ſomwhat, which thing muſt alſo bee holyly received and taken.</hi> In ſaying theſe things, hee declareth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16112:38"/>
that every Sacrament, doth, in holy things, containe ſome ſecret or myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: and that it is one thing which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth viſibly, and that it is another thing which muſt bee taken or recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved inviſibly: And what Sacraments are to be celebrated amongſt the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, hee afterwards ſheweth, ſaying: <hi>Now theſe are the Sacraments: Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and Chriſme: and the Lords bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and blood: which are therefore called Sacraments, becauſe vnder the vaile and coverture of bodily things, Gods divine power or vertue, doth ſecretly worke the efficacy or power of the ſaid Sacraments, Whence alſo it commeth to paſſe, that they are called Sacraments, of certaine ſecret powers, or holy ſolemnities in them.</hi> And afterwards he ſaith: <hi>In Greeke it it is called a myſtery, becauſe it hath in it a ſecret and hidden diſpoſition.</hi> What are we taught by theſe words, but that the Lords body and blood are therefore ſaid to be myſteries, becauſe they haue a ſecret and hidden diſpoſition, that is to ſay, are one thing in reſpect of that which they outwardly ſhew forth:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16112:38"/>
and another thing in reſpect of that, which inviſibly they worke within? And herevpon alſo they are called ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, becauſe that vnder the vaile or coverture of bodily things, Gods heavenly power and vertue doth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, but yet faithfully and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, diſpenſe, procure and worke, the ſalvation, of all ſuch as worthily and rightly receiue them.</p>
            <p>By all the things,<note place="margin">The ſum of this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Part.</note> that hitherto haue beene ſpoken, wee haue declared, that the bodie and blood of Chriſt, which in the Church are received, by the mouth of the beleevers, are figures, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their outward ſhew and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible forme, but that according to an inviſible ſubſtance, that is, according to the power of the divine word, they are verily and in deed, the body and blood of Chriſt. Wherevpon we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that as they are viſible creatures they feed the body, but that yet, throw the power of a more mightie and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſubſtance, they doe both feed and ſanctifie the minds of all faithfull people.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:16112:39"/>And now let vs looke into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond queſtion, &amp; the purpoſe or drift thereof, and let vs ſee, whether that very body, that was borne of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> that ſuffered, that was dead and buried, and that ſitteth at the right hand of the Father, be the ſame which through the myſtery of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts is daily received in the Church, by the mouths of the faithfull? Let vs enquire and ſee what S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> iudgeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this matter.<note place="margin">Ambro. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> In his Booke of Sacraments, he ſpeaketh thus; <hi>Truely it is a marveilous thing, that God did for the Fathers raine Manna from heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.25.</note> 
               <hi>and that they were daily fed with food from heaven: wherevpon it is ſaid, Man did eate the bread of Angels. And yet for all that, all they which did eate that bread in the Wilderneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.51.</note> 
               <hi>dyed. But as for this meat which thou receiveſt, yea, this liuing bread which came downe from Heaven, it miniſtreth and yeeldeth vnto thee, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of eternall life: and whoſoever ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of this bread, ſhall not die for ever, becauſe it is the body of Chriſt.</hi> Marke in what reſpect, this Doctor ſaith that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16112:39"/>
that meat, which the faithfull receiue in the Church, is Chriſts body, for he ſaith: This liuing bread, which came down from heaven, miniſtreth or yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the ſubſtance of eternal life. Doth it, as it is corporally taken, or as it is ground and chawed with the teeth, or as it is ſwallowed with the throte, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the paunch, doth it, I ſay, in theſe reſpects miniſter or yeeld the ſubſtance of everlaſting life? No veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for ſo it feedeth our fleſh that ſhall die, neither doth it giue any incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neither can it in that ſenſe be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, that whoſoever ſhall eate this bread ſhall never die, for that which the body receiveth, is corruptible, and cannot by any meanes, performe this pleaſure for the body it ſelfe, that it ſhould never die, the reaſon is, becauſe that looke whatſoever is it ſelfe, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to corruption, is not powerfull, or ſufficient, to giue eternitie. Wherefore in that bread there is life, but yet that life appeareth not to the bodily eyes, but is beheld with the eye of faith:<note place="margin">Ioh 6.50.51.</note> yea <hi>that is the liuing bread in deed, which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16112:40"/>
came downe from heaven:</hi> and of which it is truely ſaid, <hi>Whoſoever eateth it ſhall never die,</hi> and which is alſo, the Lords body.</p>
            <p>Againe, the ſame holy Doctor, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the almighty power of Chriſt, faith thus;<note place="margin">Ambro. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra. lib.</note> 
               <hi>Cannot the word of Chriſt, which was able of nothing, to make every thing that is, be ſtrong and ſufficient e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to change things that are, into that, which they were not? for it is not a greater or harder matter to create and giue new things: than to change the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of things.</hi> Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, that there is a change made in that myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, of the bodie and blood of Chriſt, and that it is done marveilouſly and wonderfully, becauſe it is done di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely and heavenly, and that it is done vnſpeakably, becauſe it is of it ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible. Now I would faine haue them, that will in this myſterie, take and vnderſtand nothing, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the hidden power that lyeth within, but iudge of the whole, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that, which viſibly and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly appeareth, I would faine haue
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16112:40"/>
theſe men, I ſay, to tell me, in what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, the change is made in this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie? If they will ſay, that it is made in reſpect of the ſubſtance of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. I anſwere, that that cannot be ſo, for in reſpect of the ſubſtance of the creatures, look whatſoever they were, before conſecration, they are even the ſame afterwards: but they were Bread and Wine before, and therefore they remaine the ſame, which is proved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we ſee, that even when they are conſecrated, they remaine in the ſame kinde and forme. Wherefore that which our faith looketh vpon, is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged inwardly, by the almightie power of the holy Ghoſt, and is it that which feedeth the ſoule, and miniſtreth or yeeldeth the ſubſtance of eternall life. Againe, the ſame Doctor, a little after ſaith: <hi>Why doeſt thou here,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. loco ſupra citato.</note> 
               <hi>in the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Chriſts bodie, ſeeke for the order of nature, ſeeing that he, being the Lord God himſelfe, was beſide, and without the courſe of nature, borne of a Virgin?</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> Here the hearer, ſcholler, or learner riſeth vp and ſaith; That, that is Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16112:41"/>
which is ſeene, and that, that is his blood which is drunke: and that wee muſt not inquire how it is made or become his body, but beleeue &amp; hold, that ſo it is become his body. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: Thou imagineſt and ſuppoſeſt, that thou thinkeſt well, but if thou di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently looke into, the nature &amp; force of the words, thou ſhalt ſee thou ſayeſt nothing. For thou affirmeſt, both that Chriſts body is ſeene, and his blood drunke: and alſo that thou doeſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully beleeue it, to be Chriſts bodie and blood: but I ſay, that theſe ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches cannot ſtand together, becauſe, if thou doeſt beleeue it, thou doeſt not yet ſee it,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>for we walke by faith, and not by ſight.</hi> And againe, if thou ſeeſt it, thou ſhouldeſt ſay I ſee it to be Chriſts very body and blood, and ſhouldeſt not ſay, I beleeue it, to be Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood. But for as much as faith beholdeth that whole thing, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that whole thing it ſelfe be, and the eye of fleſh apprehendeth or laieth hold of nothing, the ſcholler or lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſhall vnderſtand (which is alſo the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16112:41"/>
Doctors meaning) that thoſe things which are ſeene, are the body &amp; blood of Chriſt, nor in kinde and forme, but in vertue and power: wherevpon alſo he ſaith, that we muſt not in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, conſider or behold the order of nature, but reverence and eſteeme the high power of Chriſt, which maketh every thing, as he will, how he will, &amp; into what he will, and createth that which was not, and being created, changeth it into that which it was not before.</p>
            <p>The ſame Author addeth. <hi>Verily,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. loco eodem.</note> 
               <hi>that is the true fleſh of Chriſt, which was crucified, and which was buried: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this myſterie, muſt be in deede, the Sacrament of that fleſh: which thing the Lord himſelfe publiſheth, &amp; proclaimeth, ſaying: This is my body.</hi> O how dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, and how wiſely, is this diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and difference made? Of the fleſh of Chriſt, which was crucified, and which was buried, according vnto which alſo Chriſt himſelfe was both crucified &amp; buried, the Doctor ſaith, that it is the very and true fleſh of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16112:42"/>
Chriſt: but of that which is received in the Sacrament he ſayth; <hi>It is indeed the Sacrament of that true fleſh.</hi> By theſe words, diſtinguiſhing the Sacrament of his fleſh, from the truth of his fleſh, or very fleſh, in as much as in reſpect of the truth of that fleſh, which he tooke of the Virgin, he ſaid, that he was both crucified and buried. And wheras he ſaid, that the myſtery, which is at this day celebrated in the church, is the ſacrament of that very and true fleſh, in which Chriſt was crucified, he doth plainely inſtruct and teach the faithfull people, that that fleſh, in which Chriſt was both crucified and buried, is not a myſtery or Sacrament, but the truth of nature: and on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide he teacheth them, that this fleſh, which now in a myſterie doth containe the likeneſſe of that fleſh, is not that fleſh in kinde or forme, but in a Sacrament; for in kinde and forme it is Bread, but in a Sacrament it is Chriſts very true bodie,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.26. <hi>Ambr. loco citat.</hi>
               </note> as the Lord Ieſus himſelfe affirmeth, ſaying; <hi>This is my body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:16112:42"/>And the ſame Doctor in the words following, ſaith;<note place="margin">Mat. 6.31.</note> 
               <hi>What theſe words ſhould meane, mentioned in Matthew, what ſhall we eate? or what ſhall wee drinke? the holy Ghoſt, hath in another place, and after another ſort expreſſed by his Prophet, ſaying; Taſte yee, and ſee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.8.</note> 
               <hi>how gracious the Lord is: bleſſed is the man that truſteth in him.</hi> Doth that ſame Bread thinke you being taſted bodily, or that ſame Wine being drunke corporally, declare and ſhewe forth how ſweet the Lord is? No veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for whatſoever it ſavoureth it is bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, and delighteth onely the palate and throate. Shall we thinke that this is, to taſte the Lord, to wit, to feele and ſavour ſome bodily thing? No verily: for the ſpirituall taſting and ſavouring of the Lord ſtirreth vs vp, to haue lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no regard, yea to be voyde, as it were of bodily ſavouring, and in that Bread, and in that drinke, to imagine or thinke of nothing corporally, but to feele and perceiue the whole ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, becauſe <hi>the Lord is a ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.24.</note> and bleſſed is the man that truſteth in him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:16112:43"/>And againe afterwards he ſaith thus; <hi>Chriſt is in that Sacrament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. loco eodem.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe it is the body of Chriſt: wherefore it is not bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily meate, but ſpirituall foode.</hi> What could be ſpoken more plainely, more manifeſtly, or more heavenly? for he ſaith; <hi>Chriſt is in that Sacrament:</hi> and yet he ſaith not, that that Bread and that Wine is Chriſt, which if he ſhould ſay, he ſhould ſet forth Chriſt, as though he were corruptible, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to mortalitie (which be it farre from vs to thinke, much more to ſpeake) for it is certaine that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in that meate, is either bodily ſeene, or bodily taſted, all that is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to corruption. The Doctor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth theſe words, <hi>Becauſe it is the body of Chriſt.</hi> But perhaps here ſome man will ſtand vp and ſay: Behold he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly and plainly confeſſeth, that that Bread and that Wine is Chriſtes body. But withall marke I pray thee, how preſently he addeth, <hi>That it is not bodily meate but ſpirituall foode.</hi> Bring not with you therefore the ſenſe and feeling of the fleſh, for by that, nothing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16112:43"/>
either is, or can be perceived in this myſtery. It is indeed Chriſts body, howbeit, not his bodily bodie, but his ſpirituall body. It is Chriſts blood, but not his bodily blood, but his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall blood. Wherfore nothing here is to be iudged, felt, or perceived bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, but ſpiritually. It is Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, but it is not his body bodily, and it is Chriſts blood, but yet it is not his blood, bodily.</p>
            <p>Alſo afterwardes the ſame Father ſaith:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amb. eodem loco.</hi> 1 Cor. 10.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Wherevpon the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the figure of Chriſt, ſaith, that our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did eate the ſame ſpirituall meate, and did drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke: For the Lords bodie is a ſpirituall bodie, and the body of Chriſt is the body of the divine ſpirit. For Chriſt is a ſpirit, as we reade in the Lamentations of</hi> Ieremie: <hi>Chriſt the Lord is a ſpirit before our face.</hi> He hath moſt plainely taught vs, how we ſhould vnderſtand the myſtery, of the body and blood of Chriſt. For when he had ſaid, that our Fathers did eate ſpirituall meate, and did drinke ſpirituall drinke, (whereas notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16112:44"/>
there is none that doubteth, but that the <hi>Manna</hi> which they did eate, and the water which they did drinke, were bodily things) he addeth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the myſterie, which is now adminiſtred in the Church, ſhewing and determining in what reſpect it is Chriſtes bodie: <hi>For the Lords bodie</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>is a ſpirituall body.</hi> Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is indeed God: and the body which he tooke of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die that ſuffered, that was buried, that roſe againe, was certainely a very and true bodie, and the ſame alſo remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned viſible and palpable, that is to ſay, might be ſeene and felt, but that body which is called the myſterie of God, is not bodily but ſpirituall: and if it be ſpirituall, then is it not viſible or pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, that is, it cannot be ſeene or felt. Herevpon bleſſed <hi>Ambroſe</hi> addeth, ſaying; <hi>The body of Chriſt is the body of the divine ſpirit:</hi> Now the divine ſpirit is not any thing that is bodily, is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that is corruptible, or any thing that is palpable and may be felt. But this body which is celebrated and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16112:44"/>
adminiſtred in the Church, is, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the viſible kinde and forme, both corruptible and palpable. Tell me then how it can be ſaid, to be the body of the divine ſpirit? Verily no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, than in this reſpect, that it is ſpirituall, that is to ſay, in this reſpect, that it cannot be ſeene or felt, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore incorruptible.</p>
            <p>To this very end,<note place="margin">Amb. eodem loco.</note> in the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, he addeth, ſaying, <hi>Becauſe Christ is a ſpirit as we reade, Chriſt the Lord is a ſpirit before our face.</hi> By which words he plainly ſheweth in what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect it may be counted Chriſts body, to wit, in reſpect that there is in it, the ſpirit of Chriſt, that is to ſay, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the divine or heavenly word, which doth not onely feede the ſoule, but alſo purge it and make it cleane. Wherefore the ſame Author ſaith af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward; <hi>To conclude, this meate ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth our hearts, and this drinke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mans heart merry and ioyfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 104.5.</note> 
               <hi>as the Prophet ſaith.</hi> It cannot be denied, but that bodily meate, doth after a ſort ſtrengthen mans heart, and bodily
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16112:45"/>
drinke make his heart merry. But that the Doctor might ſhew what meate it is, and what drinke it is, of which he ſpeaketh, he hath plainely and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly added <hi>this meate and this drinke.</hi> What meate doth he meane, or what drinke? Forſooth Chriſts body, the body of the divine ſpirit, and that it might be the more plainely vttered, he ſaith, <hi>Chriſt is a ſpirit,</hi> of whom it is read, Chriſt the Lord is a ſpirit, before our face.</p>
            <p>By all theſe places and ſpeeches it plainely appeareth, that we ought not, or cannot, take or perceiue any thing bodily, in this meate, &amp; in this drinke: but that the whole matter muſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and weighed ſpiritually. For the ſoule (which in the place preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alledged is meant by the heart of man) is not fed with bodily meate, or bodily drinke, but it is nouriſhed, quickned, and made ſtrong, with the Word of God.<note place="margin">Ambr. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra. lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Which thing the ſelfe ſame Doctor affirmeth more plainely in his fifth Booke of Sacraments. <hi>Not this Bread</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which goeth into
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16112:45"/>
our bodies, but it is that bread of eternall life, which miniſtreth and yeeldeth ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance vnto our ſoules.</hi> And the things following in that booke or place, doe moſt manifeſtly declare that S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> ſpake not this of the common bread, but of the bread of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, for he ſpeaketh of that daily bread, which the faithfull deſire might be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, and therefore he addeth; <hi>If it be daily bread, why doeſt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it but once in a yeare, as the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans which dwell in the Eaſt, are wont to doe? Wherefore receiue that daily, which may daily profit thee: and liue ſo, that thou maieſt be found meete and worthy daily to receiue it.</hi> Wherefore it is manifeſt, of what bread he ſpeaketh, to wit, of the bread of the body of Chriſt, which ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaineth and vpholdeth the ſubſtance of the ſoule, not in reſpect as it goeth and entreth into the bodie, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect as it is Bread of everlaſting life.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, that by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this moſt learned man, wee are taught, that that bodie, in which Chriſt ſuffered, and that blood, which
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16112:46"/>
hanging vpon the Croſſe, he ſhed out of his ſide, doth very much differ from that body, which the faithfull doe daily celebrate and receiue in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of Chriſts paſſion, and from that blood, which is received by the mouth of the beleevers, ſeeing it is but a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of that blood, in and by which, the whole world was Redeemed. For this Bread and this Wine, are not Chriſts bodie and blood, in reſpect that they are to be ſeene bodily, but in reſpect that they doe ſpiritually mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and yeeld vnto vs, the ſubſtance of life. And as for that bodie, wherein Chriſt ſuffered once for all, it ſhewed forth no other kinde or forme, than that, in which it conſiſted and was. For it was truely and indeed the very ſelfe ſame, which it was when it was ſeene, which it was when it was touched, which it was when it was crucified, &amp; which it was when it was buried. In like ſort, the blood, that did guſh and flow out of his ſide, did not appeare one thing outwardly, and cover or ſhaddow another thing inwardly:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16112:46"/>
Wherefore the very blood of Chriſt, did flow from his very and true body: but now the blood of Chriſt, which the faithfull drinke vp, and his body which they eate, are one thing in kind and forme, and another thing in ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. They are one thing in that they feed the body with bodily meat: and another thing, in that they fat and feed the ſoules and mindes of men, with the ſubſtance of eternall life.</p>
            <p>Of this thing Saint <hi>Hierom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieronim in epiſt. ad Eph.</note> in his Commentary vpon <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the Epheſians, writeth thus: <hi>The blood and fleſh of Chriſt is vnderſtood two man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wayes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.55.</note> 
               <hi>For either it is that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and divine fleſh and blood, of which he himſelfe ſaith, my fleſh is meat indeed, and my blood is drinke indeed: or elſe it is put for that fleſh which was crucified, and for that blood which was ſhed with the ſouldiers ſpeare.</hi> This Doctor hath made a diſtinction, concerning the body and blood of Chriſt, and this he hath done with a very great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. For whileſt that hee ſaith, that the fleſh and blood which the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16112:47"/>
doe daily receiue, are ſpirituall things: and ſaith on the other ſide, that the fleſh which was crucified, and the blood, which was ſhed with the ſouldiers ſpeare, cannot bee affirmed to be ſpirituall or divine, hee plainely declareth, that they differ ſo much as ſpirituall and corporall things, or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and inviſible things, or as divine and humane, doe differ one of them from another, and that therefore for as much as they differ one of them from another, both of them bee not, neither indeed can bee, one and the ſelfe ſame thing. Now that ſpirituall fleſh, which is received by the mouth of the faithfull, and that ſpirituall blood which is daily offered to bee drunke of the beleevers, doe without doubt differ from that fleſh, which was crucified &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that blood which was ſhed by the ſouldiers ſpeare, as the authority of this preſent perſon alledged, doth witneſſe. Wherefore they bee not all one: For that fleſh that was crucified, was made of the fleſh of the Virgin, and was compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted or did conſiſt, of bones and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16112:47"/>
and was beſides diſtincted by the lineaments and proportions of the parts and members of mens bodies, and was through the ſpirit of a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſoule, quickned into his owne life, and fit motions agreeing thereto: But the ſpirituall fleſh, which doth ſpiritually feed the beleeving people, in reſpect of the kind or forme which it ſheweth forth outwardly, doth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made by the Artificers hand, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of certaine graines of Corne or wheat, and is not compacted of any ſinewes or bones, nor diſtincted by any diverſity of members, nor made liuely by any reaſonable ſubſtance, nor able to exerciſe any proper moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (for whatſoever in it doth mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or yeeld the ſubſtance of life, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to a ſpirituall power, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to an inviſible efficacy, and to a heavenly vertue or force) but is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in reſpect of that which is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ſeene, farre differing from that which is beleeved in the myſtery. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that fleſh of Chriſt which was crucified, did not ſhew any other thing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16112:48"/>
outwardly, then that it was inwardly, becauſe it was the very fleſh of a very man, being alſo a very body in the kinde and forme of a very body.</p>
            <p>Furthermore wee muſt conſider, that there is figured by that bread, not onely Chriſts owne body, but alſo the body of the people that beleeue in him: whereupon it is made of many graines of wheate,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 16.17</note> becauſe the bodie of the beleeving people, is through the Word of Chriſt increaſed, with many faithfull ones. Wherefore, as the bread which is Chriſts body, is received in a myſtery: ſo alſo, the members of the people, that beleeue in Chriſt, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in a myſtery. And as that bread is ſaid to bee the bodie of the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, not bodily, but ſpiritually: ſo muſt wee needs vnderſtand it to bee Chriſts bodie, not bodily, but ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually. So likewiſe in the wine, which is called Chriſts blood, water is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be mixed, and the one is not ſuffred to be offred without the other, to declare, that the people cannot bee without Chriſt, nor Chriſt without his
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16112:48"/>
people, even as the head cannot bee without the body, nor the body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the head. Wherefore the water in that Sacrament, beareth the image of people, and repreſenteth them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if that wine, being ſanctified by the office and ſervice of the Miniſters, be turned bodily into Chriſts blood, the water which is mixed together with it, muſt of neceſſity bee bodily turned into the blood of the beleeving people. For where there is but one ſanctification, and by conſequent one operation or working, yea, where there is but a like conſideration, it muſt needs then there follow, that that myſtery is like. But we ſee, that in the water, in reſpect of the body thereof, there is nothing turned, wherefore it followeth very well, that in the wine there is nothing turned bodily: What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is ſet out in the water concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the body of the people, the ſame is taken ſpiritually. Wherefore, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is ſhewed foorth in the wine, concerning Chriſts blood, the ſame muſt of neceſſity be taken ſpiritually.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:16112:49"/>Againe, the things which doe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer one of them from another, be not all one. That body of Chriſt which died, and roſe againe, and became im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.9.</note> 
               <hi>dieth not now, neither ſhall death any more now beare rule ouer it,</hi> for it is eternall and cannot now ſuffer any thing. But that which is celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and adminiſtred in the Church, is temporall, and not eternall, is corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, &amp; not incoruptible, is in the way homeward, and not in it owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: Wherefore they muſt needs dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer one of them from another, and ſo by conſequent are not all one: and if they be not all one, how is it ſaid to bee Chriſts true body, and his very blood? For if it be Chriſts body, and be truly ſo ſaid to be (as if it be Chriſts body, it muſt bee his body in truth) and if it be Chriſts body in truth or truly, then it muſt needs bee that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſts which is incorruptible, and impaſible, and ſo by conſequent eternall: Whereupon alſo it muſt of neceſſity follow, that that bodie of Chriſts which is celebrated and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16112:49"/>
in the Church, muſt be incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible and eternall: but we cannot deny, but that that thing is corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, which being changed is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into peeces, to bee received, and being broken or ground with the teeth, paſſeth into the body and belly. And yet that is one thing, which is done outwardly, and that is another thing which is inwardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved through faith. That which belongeth to the ſenſes of the body is corruptible, but that which faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth is incorruptible. Wherefore that which appeares outwardly, is not the thing it ſelfe, but the image or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of the thing, but that is the truth of the thing, and the thing it ſelfe, which is perceived &amp; vnderſtood by the minde.</p>
            <p>Hereupon bleſſed <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in his Expoſition vpon <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the body and blood of Chriſt, ſaith thus: <hi>Moſes alſo did eate Manna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Ioh. tract. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſo did Aaron, and ſo did Phiwees: yea many others did eate Manna in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, who alſo pleaſed God, and yet
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16112:50"/>
are not dead. And why ſo? becauſe they did ſpiritually vnderſtand, the viſible food, they did ſpiritually hunger after it, they did ſpiritually taſte it, that ſo they might bee ſpiritually ſatisfied and filled. For even wee alſo our ſelues, doe at this day receiue viſible food, but the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is one thing, and the vertue or power of the Sacrament is another thing.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the words following:<note place="margin">Aug. tract. eodem.</note> 
               <hi>This is the bread which came downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Manna ſignified this bread: the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of God alſo ſignified this bread. They were Sacraments: and are diverſe or differing one of them from another, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their ſignes, but are equall and like, yea all one in the matter that is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by them. Hearken what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.1.2. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>I would not haue you ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant (brethren) that all our Fathers were vnder the Clowd, and that all paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through the Sea, and were all bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto Moſes, in the Clowd and in the Sea, and did all eate the ſame ſpirituall meate, and did all drinke the ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall drinke. Verily they had the ſame ſpirituall both meate and drinke, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16112:50"/>
bodily both meate and drinke, for they had Manna, and we another thing, and yet they had the ſame ſpirituall thing that we haue. And the Apoſtle addeth: and they did all drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke. They drunke one thing, and wee another, but that was in reſpect of viſible kinde or forme, and yet they both ſignified one thing by ſpirituall power. For how o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe could it be the ſame drinke. They drank</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of the ſpirituall rock that followed them: and the rocke was Chriſt. From thence came the bread, from thence came the drinke. The rocke was Chriſt in ſign &amp; figure, but the very &amp; true Christ is in word and in fleſh.</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">Aug. tract. eodem.</note> in the ſame place: <hi>This is the bread that came downe from heaven, ſo that whoſoever ſhall eate of it, ſhall not dye: but yet hee muſt eate that, which appertaineth to the vertue and power of the Sacrament, and not that onely which appertaineth to the viſible Sacrament. And ſuch a one is hee as eateth inwardly, and not outwardly on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and as eateth the ſame in his heart through faith, and not that pearceth or preſſeth it with his teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:16112:51"/>And in another place of his ſaide Expoſition vpon <hi>Iohn,</hi> bringing in our Saviours words, hee ſpeaketh thus:<note place="margin">Aug. in Ioh. tract <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Doth this offend you, that I ſaid, behold, I giue you my fleſh to eate, and my blood to drinke? What then if ye ſhall ſee the Sonne of man aſcend vp, where he was before? What meaneth this? Doth hee by this ſpeech looſe that which moved them? Doth hee by ſo ſaying open that wherewith they were offended? Yea ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, and that fully alſo, if they could haue vnderſtood it. For they thought, that he would haue given his body, but hee ſaid that hee would goe vp into heaven, and that whole as he was: as though he ſhould ſay: When yee ſhall ſee the Sonne of man aſcending vp where hee was before, at the leaſt even then yee ſhall know, that hee will not giue his body after ſuch a manner and faſhion, as you imagine and fantaſie: yea, and even then alſo yee ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that his grace is not conſumed or eaten vp by bytings and morſels. For the Lord himſelfe ſaith: It is the ſpirit that quickeneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing. And after that hee had vttered many
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16112:51"/>
words and ſentences, hee againe addeth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. tract. eodem.</hi> Rom. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoever (ſaith the Apoſtle) hath not the ſpirit of Chriſt, the ſame is none of his. Wherefore it is the ſpirit that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, the fleſh profiteth nothing. The words that I haue ſpoken vnto you, are ſpirit and life. What meaneth this that they are ſpirit and life? That is to ſay, they muſt be ſpiritually vnderstood. Haſt thou vnderſtood them ſpiritually: then are they ſpirit and life to thee. Haſt thou vnderſtood them carnally: yea even ſo are they ſpirit and life, but not vnto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the authority of this Doctor, handling the Lords words, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Sacrament of his body and blood, wee are plainely taught, that thoſe words of the Lord muſt bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood ſpiritually, and not carnally, even as himſelfe ſaith:<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.63.</note> 
               <hi>The words which I ſpeake vnto you are ſpirit and life:</hi> yea even thoſe words verily which hee ſpake concerning the eating of his fleſh, and the drinking of his blood: For he ſpeaketh of thoſe words where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with his Diſciples were offended. Wherefore, to the end they might
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16112:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:16112:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:16112:53"/>
not be offended, the heavenly Maſter or Teacher, calleth them back fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fleſh to the ſpirit, and from bodily ſight, to inviſible vnderſtanding. We ſee therefore in what reſpect that meat of the Lords body, and that drinke of his blood, are truly and indeed his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and truly and indeed his blood, to wit, in reſpect that they are ſpirit and life.</p>
            <p>Moreover: ſuch things as bee all one, are contained in or vnder one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition. Now it is affirmed, of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and true body of Chriſt, that hee is very God and very man: God as hee was begotten of the father from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all beginnings: and man, as hee was towards the end of the world, conceived and borne of the Virgine <hi>Mary.</hi> But theſe things cannot bee ſaid of that body of Chriſt, which by a myſtery is celebrated and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the Church, and yet it is after a certaine manner knowne to bee Chriſts body: now that manner is in figure and repreſentation, that ſo the truth, and the thing it ſelfe, may bee
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16112:53"/>
the better perceived.</p>
            <p>In theſe prayers, which are ſayd af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the myſtery of the body and blood of Chriſt, and whereunto the people anſwer, Amen, thus it is vttered with the Prieſts voyce: <hi>Wee, that doe take or receiue the pledge of everlaſting life, doe humbly beſeech thee to grant, that we may with a manifeſt and plaine parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king receiue that, which we touch, in the image or repreſentation of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now wee know that a pledge and an image or repreſentation, appertaine to another thing, that is to ſay, haue reſpect not to themſelues, but to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing. For a pledge is a pledge of that thing, for the pledging where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it is given, and not the thing it ſelfe, as likewiſe an image is the image of that thing, the likeneſſe whereof it doth repreſent or ſhew forth. For theſe things doe ſignifie the thing it ſelfe, whoſe picture and pledge they are, and yet for all that, they doe not very manifeſtly declare the things themſelues. Which ſeeing it is ſo, it
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16112:54"/>
plainely appeareth, that this body and blood, are the pledge, and (as it were) the picture, or repreſentation of a thing that ſhall be, to the end, that that which is now ſhewed by a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, may in time hereafter to come, be, by manifeſtation, or manifeſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed. Wherevpon, I conclude, that if now they ſignifie, and in time to come ſhall make manifeſt, or lay open, that then, that is one thing, which is done and performed now, and that that is another thing, which ſhall in time to come, be manifeſted and layd open. Wherefore, that which the Church celebrateth and adminiſtreth, is both the body and blood of Chriſt, but yet as a pledge, and (as it were) the picture, or repreſentation. But then it ſhall be the truth, when as now, not the pledge, nor the picture, or repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the thing ſhall appeare, but the truth of the thing it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Alſo in another place of the ſayde prayers; <hi>We beſeech thee Lord to graunt that thy Sacraments may worke that in vs, which they doe containe, that looke what
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:16112:54"/>
we now adminiſter and receiue in forme, we may alſo receiue it in the truth of the things.</hi> He ſaith, that theſe things are celebrated and done, in ſhew &amp; forme, and not in truth, that is, in ſimilitude or likeneſſe, and not in the declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the thing it ſelfe. Now the forme and ſhew of a thing, and the veritie or truth of the ſelfe ſame thing, differ one of them from another. Wherefore that body and blood, which is celebrated and received in the Church, differeth from that bodie and blood, which is known to be now glorified in Chriſts body, thorow his Reſurrection. And the former of theſe two bodies is a pledge and figure: and this latter is the very truth it ſelfe, for the former is celebrated and adminiſtred, till ſuch time, as we may come to the other: but when we ſhall once come to this latter, the former ſhall be removed and taken away. Wherefore it appreareth, that they are by a very great difference ſundred one of them from the other: yea, looke what difference there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the pledge and thing for which
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16112:55"/>
the pledge is given, and betweene an Image, or the thing whoſe Image it is, or betweene the forme and ſhew of a thing, and the truth it ſelfe, ſo much difference there is, betweene the one and the other. Thus we ſee, that that myſterie of the bodie and blood of Chriſt, which the faithfull doe nowe receiue in the Church, doth much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, &amp; is farre ſevered from that body, which was borne of the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> which ſuffered, which was buried, which roſe againe, which aſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heaven, and which ſitteth at the right hand of the Father. For that which is celebrated &amp; received, while we are in the way of this life, muſt be ſpiritually received and vnderſtoode; for Faith beleeveth the thing which it ſeeth not, &amp; layeth hold of that which doth ſpiritually feed the ſoule, and make glad the heart, and giveth eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, and incorruption, whileſt we looke not vpon that, which feedeth the body, or is preſſed with the teeth, or is broken in peeces, but that only which is ſpiritually received in faith: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16112:55"/>
that bodie, in which Chriſt ſuffered and roſe againe, is his owne very bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which he tooke of the body of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which alſo was palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and viſible, yea, and that after his Reſurrection; even as he himſelfe ſaith vnto the Diſciples:<note place="margin">Luke 24.38.39.</note> 
               <hi>Why are yee trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled? and wherefore doe thoughts and doubts ariſe in your hearts? Beholde my handes and my feete, for it is I my ſelfe. Handle me and ſee, for a ſpirit hath not fleſh and bones as yee ſee me haue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs heare alſo what bleſſed <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentius</hi> writeth in his Booke of Faith; <hi>Looke that thou doe moſt ſtedfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fulgen. de fide.</note> 
               <hi>and at no hand doubt that the onely begotten Word of God became fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>and offered vp himſelfe for vs as an offering, and a ſacrifice, of a ſweet ſmelling ſavour vnto God. Vnto whom, with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, the Patriarkes, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Prieſtes, did in the time of the olde Teſtament, offer vp Beaſts and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice them: and vnto whom alſo, with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt (with whom he is of one and the ſelfe ſame God-head) the holy Catholique Church being diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:16112:56"/>
throughout the whole world, ceaſeth not in faith, and loue, to offer vp, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Bread and Wine. For in thoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of fleſh and Beaſts, there was a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of Chriſtes fleſh, which even he himſelfe being without ſinne ſhould offer for our ſinnes: and of his blood alſo, which he ſhould ſhed for the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes: but in this ſacrifice of Bread and Wine, there is a thankeſgiving for, and a remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of that fleſh of Chriſt, which he offered vp for vs: and of that blood, which he himſelfe, being very God, did ſhed for vs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> 
               <hi>of which S.</hi> Paul <hi>ſpeaketh in the</hi> Acts <hi>of the</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>and in the</hi> xx. <hi>Chapter of the ſaid booke, ſaying: Take heed vnto your ſelues, and to all the flocke, whereof the holy Ghoſt hath made you Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops or over-ſeers, to governe the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his owne blood. Wherefore there was in the former ſacrifices figuratiuely ſignified, that that ſhould be given to vs: but there is in this ſacrifice evidently and plainely decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, what is given vnto vs.</hi> Now the Doctor in ſaying, that there was in thoſe ſacrifices ſignified, what ſhould
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16112:56"/>
be given vnto vs, and that in this ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, there was declared what was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vnto vs alreadie, he doth plainely declare, that as thoſe ſacrifices had the figure of things to come, ſo our ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is a figure of things that are paſt. By which ſpeeches he hath moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently declared, what great difference there is, betweene that bodie wherein Chriſt ſuffered, and this body which is celebrated and adminiſtred in the remembrance of his Paſſion, or death. For that body wherein he ſuffered, was his proper, and very or true body, having no myſticall or figuratiue mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in it: But this latter is a myſticall bodie, ſhewing one thing outwardly in figure, and inwardly repreſenting another thing, thorowe the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and apprehenſion of faith.</p>
            <p>Moreover, let vs adde and put downe one other teſtimony of that reverent Father, <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> which ſhall both warrant the truth and credit of our ſayings, and make an end of our Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſpeech. In a certaine Sermon,<note place="margin">Aug. de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra. altar. Serm.</note> which he made to the people concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16112:57"/>
the Sacrament of the Altar, thus he ſaith. <hi>The thing which you ſee on Gods Altar, you ſaw the ſame the night that is paſt: but as yet yee haue not heard, what it is, what it meaneth, and of how great a matter it containeth the Sacrament. The thing which you ſee is bread, and the cup, which thing alſo your owne eyes doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto you: but as concerning that wherein your faith requireth to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, the Bread is the body of Chriſt, and the cup is his blood. Truely this is ſhortly ſayd, and it may be perhaps ſufficient for faith, but yet faith alwayes needeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>For the Prophet ſayth, Vnleſſe yee beleeue, yee ſhall not vnderſtand. You may peradventure ſay vnto me; Thou biddeſt vs beleeue, but yet we ſay, declare it vnto vs, that we may vnderſtand. For ſuch a thought may ariſe in ſome mans mind: We know from whom our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt tooke his fleſh, to wit, of the Virgin</hi> Mary: <hi>hee being an Infant, did ſucke, and was nouriſhed, and did grow and came to mans age, he ſuffered perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution at the Iewes handes, he was han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vpon a tree, he was killed, he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16112:57"/>
from the Croſſe, he was buried, the third day he roſe againe, he aſcended into heaven, even what day pleaſed him, thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he carryed vp his body, from thence ſhall he come to iudge the quicke and the dead, and he is there now ſitting at the right hand of the Father. How then is the bread his body? and the cup, or that which is contained in the cup, how is it his blood? Theſe things (good brethren) are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called Sacraments, becauſe one thing is ſeene in them, and another thing vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood: that which is ſeene, hath a bodily kinde, forme, and ſhew: but that which is vnderſtood, hath ſpirituall fruit.</hi> The reverend Authour in ſpeaking theſe things inſtructeth vs, what wee ought to thinke and hold, both concerning the Lords owne bodie, which was borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and ſitteth now at the right hand of GOD, and in which he ſhall come to judge the quicke and the dead: and alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that body, which is ſet on the Altar, and whereof the people are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers. That body is ſound and whole, and is not divided by any cutting, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16112:58"/>
covered with any figures: but this bodie which is ſet vpon the Lords Table, is both a figure, becauſe it is a Sacrament, and alſo as it is outwardly ſeene, hath a bodily kinde and forme that feedeth the body, but as it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly vnderſtood, it hath a ſpirituall fruit, which quickeneth the ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra. altar. Serm. <hi>1 Cor. 12.27.</hi>
               </note>And the ſame Doctor, minding to ſpeake ſomewhat more plainely and manifeſtly, of this myſticall body, in the words following, ſaith thus; <hi>If yee will therefore vnderſtand what Chriſtes body meanes, heare the Apoſtles, ſaying: Yee are the body of Chriſt, and members for your part. If then yee be the bodie of Chriſt, and members for your part, your myſterie is ſet on the Lords Table, and yee receiue the myſtery of the Lord. You anſwere: Amen, to that thing which you your ſelues be, and by ſo anſwering, you ſubſcribe and conſent to the ſame. Thou heareſt then Chriſtes body, and thou an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereſt, Amen: be a member of the body of Chriſt, that ſo thy Amen may be true and right. But wherefore is this done in bread? In this matter we will bring forth
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16112:58"/>
nothing of our owne deviſe, let vs rather heare the Apoſtle himſelfe vtter his minde, when ſpeaking of this Sacrament, he ſayth, we that are many, are one bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.17.</note> 
               <hi>and one body, &amp;c.</hi> This holy man <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth ſufficiently inſtruct vs, that as Chriſtes bodie is ſignified by the Bread which is ſet vpon the Altar, ſo alſo there is thereby ſignified by the bodie of the people that receiveth it, manifeſtly thereby declaring, that that is Chriſtes proper or owne body, in which he was borne of the Virgin, in which he ſucked, in which he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, in which be died, in which he was buried, in which he roſe againe, in which he aſcended into Heaven, in which he ſitteth at the right hand of the Father, and in which he ſhall come to judge the quicke and the dead: Whereas that which is ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lords Table, conteineth the myſterie of the other, even as it doth likewiſe containe, the myſterie of the beleeving people, the Apoſtle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe witneſſing the ſame, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Wee that are many, are one bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.17.</note>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:16112:59"/>
               <hi>and one body in Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your wiſdome (moſt noble Prince) may perceiue and vnderſtand, that I haue both by the teſtimonies of the ſacred Scriptures and by the ſayings of the holy Fathers, faithfully alledged and layd downe, moſt evidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, and plainely prooved, that that bread which is called Chriſts bodie, and that cup which is called Chriſts blood, is a figure, becauſe it is a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery: and alſo that there is no ſmall difference, betweene that his body, which is ſo in a myſtery, and that his body, which ſuffer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and was buried, and roſe againe, becauſe in that was the very proper bodie of our Saviour, neither was there in it, any figure or or ſignification, but the manifeſtation and plaineneſſe of the thing it ſelfe was knowne, as alſo the beleevers at this day, doe deſire the ſight thereof: for that is our head, and when wee ſee it,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.30.</note> our deſire ſhall be ſatisfied: <hi>for he and the Father are one,</hi> not in reſpect that our Saviour hath a body, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>the fulneſſe of the godhead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.9.</note>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:16112:59"/>
which dwelt in Chriſt, as hee was man. Whereas in this, which is cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated and adminiſtred by a myſtery, there is a figure not onely of Chriſts owne body, but alſo of the body of the people, that beleeue in Chriſt: for it beareth the figure of both the bodies, that is to ſay, both of Chriſt bodie which ſuffered, and roſe again, and of the people, that are in Chriſt through Baptiſme borne againe, and quickened from the dead.</p>
            <p>Hereunto let vs adde alſo, that this bread, and this cup, which is called the body and blood of Chriſt, doth lieuely repreſent or ſet out the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the Lords paſſion or death, even as hee himſelfe hath ſayd in the Goſpell:<note place="margin">Luk. 22.19.</note> 
               <hi>Doe ye this in remembrance of mee:</hi> which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding, ſaith:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.26.</note> 
               <hi>So often as yee ſhall eate of this bread, and drinke of this cup, yee ſhall ſhew forth the Lords death till hee come.</hi> Here we are taught by our Saviour, &amp; by the holy Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that that bread, and that wine, which is ſet on the Altar, is there ſet
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:16112:60"/>
for a figure or remembrance of the Lords death, to the end it might call back to our remembrance, that which hath beene done in time paſt, that ſo wee being made mindefull of that his paſſion, might by it be made partakers of Gods gifts and graces, by which alſo wee are delivered from death, knowing this, that when wee ſhall come to the ſight and beholding of Chriſt, we ſhall haue no need of ſuch inſtruments and meanes, thereby to be put in remembrance, what his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurable and infinite goodneſſe hath endured for vs: the reaſon is, becauſe that <hi>When wee ſhall behold him face to face,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12.</note> wee ſhall be put in minde, not by any outward admonition of temporall things, but we ſhall behold him in the very contemplation and ſight of the truth it ſelfe, and to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed how we ought to giue thanks to the author of our ſaluation.</p>
            <p>And yet I would haue no man thinke, that becauſe wee ſpeake thus, that therefore the faithfull doe not in the myſtery of the Sacrament, receiue
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:16112:60"/>
the Lords body and blood, becauſe faith receiveth that thing, not which the eye ſeeth, but that which the hart beleeveth: for it is a ſpirituall meate, and a ſpirituall drinke, ſpiritually fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſoule, and giving the life of everlaſting fulneſſe, even as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelfe commending and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out this myſtery, ſaith:<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.63.</note> 
               <hi>It is the ſpirit that quickeneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I being a man of very ſmall gifts, and deſiring to yeeld obedience vnto your Excellencies commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, haue preſumed and vndertaken to diſpute, or reaſon of no ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: wherein I haue not followed the preſumption of mine owne thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king or iudgement, but regarded ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the authority of the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: which, if your Highnes ſhall allow, as ſpoken Catholikely &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly, impute it I pray you to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts and worthineſſe of your owne zeale and religion, which was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed (having for a while layd aſide the glory of your Kingly magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence)
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:16112:61"/>
to demand an anſwer concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the truth, of ſuch a poore and baſe perſon as I am. But if happily theſe things ſhall not pleaſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light you, aſcribe it vnto my folly and vnskilfulneſſe, which could not ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually declare that which your Highneſſe wiſhed, and I my ſelfe greatly deſired.</p>
            <trailer>Here endeth Bertrams Booke, concerning the Body and Blood of the Lord.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:16112:61"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IN the Epiſtle]</hi> Whether he ſpurious, <hi>(reade)</hi> whether he be ſpurious.</p>
            <list>
               <head>In the Preface next following.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>PAge 2.</hi> Charlemayne the Great, <hi>(reade)</hi> Charles the Great.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page 7.</hi> Trithenius <hi>(reade)</hi> Trithemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Page 9.</hi> Sendeth greeting <hi>(reade)</hi> ſend greeting.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the Booke of <hi>Bertram.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>FOl. 5.</hi> Outwardly locked vp <hi>(reade)</hi> outwardly looked vpon.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fol. 9.</hi> In colour or in favour <hi>(reade)</hi> in colour or in ſavour.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
